<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the devotions of the Church of Rome, especially, as compared with those of the Church of England in which it is shewn, that whatever the Romanists pretend, there is not so true devotion among them, nor such rational provision for it, nor encouragement to it, as in the church established by law among us.</title>
            <author>Stanley, William, 1647-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12306462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12306462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 926:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the devotions of the Church of Rome, especially, as compared with those of the Church of England in which it is shewn, that whatever the Romanists pretend, there is not so true devotion among them, nor such rational provision for it, nor encouragement to it, as in the church established by law among us.</title>
                  <author>Stanley, William, 1647-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Stanley. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Devotion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING THE DEVOTIONS OF THE <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> Eſpecially, as compared with thoſe of the CHURCH of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> In which it is ſhewn, That whatever the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> pretend, there is not ſo true <hi>Devotion</hi> among them, nor ſuch rational Proviſion for it, nor Encouragement to it, as in the Church eſtabliſhed by Law among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:59271:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>P. 13. l. 18. r. Monkery. p. 16. l. 29. r. Aſſiſtance. p. 25. l. 20. r. Seale for Seat. p. 37. l. 25. r. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. p. 40. l. 10. r. deſtroy for remove. p. 45. l. 31. r. puniſhed for promiſed. p. 46. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. depending. p. 47. l. 30, 31. r. Deciſions for Deviſions. p. 48. l. 29. r. ſevere for ſecure. p. 50. l. 31. r., for: p. 51. l. 21. r. loth for loath. p. 63. l. 22. r. eſpecial for eſpecially. p. 64. l. 27. r. (and for (or. p. 65. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. Camere for Camaerae.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59271:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the DEVOTIONS OF THE <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is certainly one of the greateſt Commendations that can be given of any Church, or Body of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that a man can with Truth affirm of it, that the Doctrines which they profeſs, the Rules and Orders under which they live, that the Frame and Conſtitution of the Church tendeth directly to make men more pious and devout, more penitent and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, more heavenly minded, and every way of better Lives than the way and profeſſion of other Chriſtians: For to work men up to this holy Frame and Diſpoſition was one of the main deſigns of the Goſpel of Chriſt, which intends to govern mens Actions, and reform their Temper, as well as to inform their Underſtandings, and direct their Belief. And in this particular it differs much from all the <hi>Ethicks</hi> of the learned Heathen. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they deſign'd eſpecially to exalt the Paſſions, and to raiſe up the Mind above it ſelf, by commending the high and pompous Vertues, thereby to ſtir men up to great Deſigns, and to appear bold and braving in the affairs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59271:3"/>of this Life; the Goſpel is moſt frequent in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the humble lowly and mortifying Vertues, which would reduce the Mind to it ſelf, and keep Men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in due Bounds, and teach them how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards God, and to live in a due regard to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life.</p>
            <p>Now there is ſcarcely any thing which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth more often urge for her ſelf, or with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Confidence pretend to excel the Church of <hi>England</hi> in, than by endeavouring to perſwade, that the Frame of their Church is more fitted <hi>for the exciting of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and a good Life than ours is. And ſo they will boaſt of their Severe, Rules and Orders, the Auſterities of their Faſts and Penances, the ſtrict and mortifyed Lives, the conſtancy and inceſſancy of Devotions uſed among them; and would thence inferre, that that muſt needs be the beſt Religion, or way of ſerving God in which theſe Practiſes are enjoyn'd and obſerved, That <hi>the Tree muſt needs be good by ſuch excellent Fruits;</hi> and that if all other Arguments fail, yet they ſay they have this to ſhow for themſelves, that in their Communion there is at leaſt ſomewhat more like that great Self-denial and Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo often made neceſſary under the Goſpel, than is to be found in the Reformed Churches, or particularly in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Now laying aſide all Diſputes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Points of Doctrine, in controverſie between them and us, in which it hath been abundantly ſhewn, that they err in <hi>matters of Faith;</hi> and that in what they differ from us, they differ alſo from the Scripture, and the true Church of Chriſt in all the beſt Ages; I'll confine my ſelf to examine their <hi>Pretence to Devotion,</hi> where I doubt not but it will ſufficiently appear, that they are as much deficient alſo in <hi>Regularity of Practice;</hi> that there is not that true Foundation laid for ſuch Devotion as God accepts, nor that ſtrict Proviſion made for it, nor that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59271:3"/>real Practice of it which they would make us believe; but that even the beſt which they pretend to, is ſuch as doth by no means befit a truly Chriſtian Spirit,</p>
            <p>I'll diſcourſe in this Method:
<list>
                  <item>1. I'll inſtance in the ſeveral Expreſſions of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Motives to it, or Aſſiſtances of it, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretends to, and on which ſhe is uſed to magnifie her ſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. I will alledge the juſt Exceptions which we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch their Pretences.</item>
                  <item>3. And then ſhow that they are ſo far from encouraging true Devotion, that many things both in their Doctrine and Diſcipline directly tend to the Deſtruction of it.</item>
                  <item>4. I'll ſhew what excellent Proviſion is made in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the due exerciſe of all the parts of Devotion, and what Streſs is laid on it, and on a good Life among us.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Though Devotion is properly and chiefly in the mind, a due ſenſe of God and Religion, yet it is not ſufficient if it ſtop there: For there are certain outward Acts which are either in themſelves natural and proper Expreſſions, or elſe are ſtrictly required of us by God, as Duties of Religion, and Evidences of the devout tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of our Minds; and theſe are called Acts of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And all the Commendation that can be given of any Church, on Account of Devotion, muſt be either, that there is a true Foundation laid for it in mens Minds, or conſtant Proviſion made for the due Exerciſe of it, all neceſſary Encouragement given to it, and a ſuitably, ſtrict and regular Practice of it obſervable among them. And there are ſeveral things which are not at all inſiſted on by us, which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſt of, as ſerving to ſome or all of theſe purpoſes, which I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent as fairly as I can, that we may ſee what there is in that Church that doth anſwer ſuch great pretences.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59271:4"/>
            <p> For it is obſerved that they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> oftentimes inſtead of <hi>diſpute,</hi> endeavour to work on our People, and too often prevail, by appealing to matters of <hi>Practice,</hi> viſible to every ones Eye; an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to which men need not uſe their Reaſon, but their Senſe; and this will, (ſay they) ſufficiently convince any of the excellency of our way. <q>For here are ſeveral things uſed as Inſtances and Expreſſions of <hi>Devotion,</hi> very acceptable to God, and ſuitable to a good Chriſtian Temper, which are either not at all uſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or at leaſt not in that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and Meaſure, and yet all thoſe that are uſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſay they, are uſed among us: For we not only enjoyn, and practiſe conſtant uſe of Prayers public and private, together with Reading and Preaching of the Word, Sacraments, and what ever is uſed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but we have beſides ſeveral things which are as well proper Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Devotion, as Helps and Aſſiſtances which are not uſed among the Proteſtants:</q> The Principal things which they urge are ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. They blame the Reformation in general, as well as the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the want of Monaſteries and ſuch other Religious Houſes, which are ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Countries, where Holy Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being ſhut up, and having bid adieu to the World, live as in Heaven in conſtant Exerciſe of praiſing of God Night and Day, and of praying to him for the Church and State, and particular Chriſtians, as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and who are not only ſo beneficial to the World, by the conſtancy of their Prayers, but alſo by their Example putting others in mind of Religion, and of <hi>doing likewiſe;</hi> and by the ſeverity of their lives, as to Diet, Garbe, and other Circumſtances, live in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Practice of that ſelf-denyal which is commanded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59271:4"/>in Scripture, and was ſo practiſed by Holy Men almoſt from the beginning of Chriſtianity; and are as it were conſtant Preachers of Holineſs and Mortification, who tho' they do indeed ſtay here in the World below, yet converſe not in it, but are in ſome Senſe out of it, and live above it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſometimes alſo boaſt of the extraordinary Charity, and Liberality to all good and Holy Uſes preſſed and practiſed among them, which is but ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly uſed, ſay they, among the Proteſtants; Eſpecially their exceſſive Expence and Coſt in building and endowing Monaſteries, erecting Churches, Chappels and Croſſes, their ſo pompous adorning the Places de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the Worſhip of God, beſides their Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſſiſtance, and relief which they afford to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Living, and the Souls of the Dead; and no Man can deny but Charity is a certain Evidence, as well as a great branch and duty of true Religion and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sometimes they glory in the great number of Saints commemorated in their Church, and dying in the Communion of it, and urge them as a forcible Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to others, and a mighty incentive to Devotion; they think alſo it redounds much to the Honour, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of their Church to have had ſuch glorious Members of it, and twit us as they think ſeverely, when they ask us what Saints we have of our Church, and wonder eſpecially that we ſhould obſerve ſo few Feſtivals and Holidays; whereas the very many days ſet apart in their Church in memory of their ſeveral Saints, they think not only afford proper Occaſions, for all Acts of Religion; but are a ſign of their being leſs addicted to this World, when ſo great a part of their time is ſpent in the Service of God, and that Piety and Devotion are a conſiderable part of their Buſineſs and Employment.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59271:5"/> 4. They urge alſo the multitude of Pictures and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſeveral Famous Men and Women, who have in an eminent manner ſerved and pleaſed God, and been inſtrumental in converting the World, as very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Aſſiſtances of a Mans Devotion; inſtructing ſome, they being the Books of the Unlearned, and ſenſibly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting and alluring all to the Imitation of the Perſons whom they repreſent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Sometimes they commend their Church for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, and other Acts of Severity and Mortification, uſed not only by the <hi>Monks</hi> and Regulars, but by all ſorts of Men, according to the Rules of their Church, on ſet days of the Week or Seaſons of the Year; as well as ſuch Auſterities as are enjoyned by their Confeſſors, by way of Penance; their going bare-foot and bare-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Proceſſions, their whipping and laſhing themſelves, their drawing great Chains and Weights after them, as great and proper Inſtances of Self-denial and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They place alſo a great Deal of Religion in Philgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, which the more Devout ſort take, and ſpend their Eſtates, and ſometimes their Lives in, to <hi>Jeruſalem, Rome, Loretto, Mount-ferrat,</hi> to St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> at <hi>Canterbury</hi> St. <hi>Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid</hi>'s Well, or ſome ſuch other places where ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Perſon hath lived, or ſome ſtrange Relique is left, or where they reckon God hath on ſome Occaſion or other wonderfully manifeſted himſelf; and they reckon that the very viſiting or kiſſing theſe, are either an argument of truly Devout Minds, or that which will make them ſo. And their Manuals or Books which their Prieſts give into the Peoples Hands, do not fail by all the art imaginable, to endeavour to ſcrew up Mens Devotion, even to rapture and extaſie in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of theſe Practiſes and Orders, even as if they would have us believe that there is no true Religion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59271:5"/>and Devotion without theſe, and that where there are theſe things practiſed, it is a certain Sign that the mind is affected as it ought, and Piety flouriſheth in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Degree.</p>
            <p>And beſides theſe Matters of Practice, there are alſo ſeveral Doctrines, and Opinions peculiar to themſelves, whichthey reckon do naturally tend to the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true Devotion. As,</p>
            <p n="7">7. Their Doctrine concerning the Interceſſion of Saints for us, and the Advantage of Invocation or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to them, and that we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> want one of the greateſt Encouragements to Prayer and Devotion that can be, who neither own nor make uſe of theſe Helps, and therefore that we cannot have ſuch hope of Succeſs and Bleſſing as they have.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Their Doctrine concerning the Merit of Good Works and Supererogation, is of the ſame Nature, in their eſteem: For the more Worth you ſuppoſe in any Action, the greater Incouragement is there to the Performance of it, and therefore ſurely it muſt be a moſt irreſiſtible motive to Devotion, to perſwade men that the worth and value of it is ſuch, as that you may by it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Heaven not only for your ſelves, but for others alſo.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Their belief of Purgatory, and of the validity of Prayers for the Dead, doth naturally tend to excite men to Devotion, ſay they; for here is a greater Scope and Occaſion for our Prayers, we may hope to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to more good, more Perſons to be relieved and helped by our Prayers, than are ſuppoſed in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. And eſpecially their Doctrine and Practice of Confeſſion, Penance and Abſolution, they look on as ſo neceſſary to Devotion, that it is a wonder with them that there ſhould be any ſhow of it, where theſe are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59271:6"/>not received and practiſed: For a particular Confeſſion of all Sins to a Prieſt being ſo ſtrictly required, they ſay is the readieſt way to bring men to a Senſe of and ſhame for their Sins; and Penance being alſo impoſed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on them, will ſurely make Men to be more afraid of ſinning again when they ſee it muſt coſt them ſo dear, and that they may not deſpair or deſpond, by Reaſon of the Multitude or Weight of their former Sins, but may be encouraged to ſtrive more earneſtly againſt Sin for the future, the Prieſt gives them Abſolution of what is paſſed, at the ſame time encouraging their hope, as well as exciting their fear, and endeavouring by the ſame Method both to allure, to force and to ſhame Men into Amendment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly they inſiſt much alſo on the Validity of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations, the Truth and Succeſſion Unity and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, of their Church, and the Obedience that is pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Rules and Orders of it, as mighty Helps and Aſſiſtances, and Encouragements to Devotion; when they are ſo ſure of the Sacraments being duly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and all other Acts of Authority rightly performed, when the Laws of the Church, for the Puniſhment of Offenders are duly executed, and when the Church hath Power to oblige all to an Uniform and Regular Practice.</p>
            <p>All theſe things, ſay they, do either encourage and excite men to Devotion, or aſſiſt or direct them in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it, give more room or afford better Occaſions for it, or elſe ſhow more fully the Neceſſity of ſuch and ſuch parts of it then what is received and practiſed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> that wants theſe wanteth alſo much of the <hi>Occaſion, Matter,</hi> Opportunities and Arguments for Devotion: ſo that lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide all diſputes concerning Articles of Faith, they doubt not but it will be readily granted, that at leaſt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59271:6"/>they are a more <hi>devout People;</hi> whatever their <hi>Belief</hi> is, their <hi>Practice</hi> is more agreable to that Self-denial and Mortification commanded in Scripture; that God is more conſtantly and reverently ſerved among them than he is among us; that they take more Pains, are at more Coſt and Trouble in the Worſhip of God, which they think is an Inſtance of a good religious mind, and will be moſt ſecure of God's Acceptance.</p>
            <p>Theſe are, I think indeed, the moſt that they do urge for themſelves in this point, and there is ſomething of appearance of Truth in all this. Moſt of theſe Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſuch as may perhaps be very taking at firſt ſight with ſome people, they having a ſhew of Regularity, Strictneſs and Severity, or elſe of being proper Helps and Aſſiſtances of Devotion: For Men are wont to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire any thing that looks odd or big, eſpecially if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have but the Confidence highly to praiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol it. But if we examine them, we ſhall find them to fall infinitely ſhort of ſuch ſpecious Pretences; ſome of them to be unlawful, and thoſe that are good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to be ſome way or other ſpoiled in the uſe of them; always they err in ſome material part or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and taken all together, they have nothing in them which evidence any true devout Temper, either deſigned to be wrought by the Church, or actually work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the People: Much leſs do they beſpeak greater Devotion than is required and practiſed in our Church.</p>
            <p>For it hath been well obſerved by the judicious Sir <hi>Edwin Sandys,</hi> that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſo contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved its Rules and Orders, as rather to comply with, and fit every Temper and Inclination good or bad, than to work any real good effect on any. And therefore as it hath ſeveral things which openly agree with, and pleaſe the profane and debauch'd; ſo it muſt be granted, that it hath ſomewhat alſo to ſuit with and gratifie the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59271:7"/>melancholly Temper, where the devoutly diſpoſed may find ſomewhat an agreeable Retreat: And therefore one would be apt to ſuſpect that the moſt ſtrict and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere of their Orders, were kept up rather out of a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick end, to pleaſe and quiet the People, than really to advance true Piety to God and Devotion. But however it is plain, that taking the whole Frame of that Church together, it doth not deſign to promote ſerious and true Devotion; but only to make a Noiſe, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo to do. For when I ſee the ſame Church, tho' ſometimes ſeeming to countenance the utmoſt Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as neceſſary, yet at other times to give all Liberty, and let the Reins looſe to all kind of Debauchery, I have juſt reaſon to fear they are not in earneſt for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: For all ſuch irregular Heats, are a fign of bad Principles, or a diſtemper'd Conſtitution. Juſt as if I ſhould ſee the ſame perſon ſometimes deſperately diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and debauch'd, and at other times intolerably ſtrict and ſevere, and this interchangeably and often, I ſhall much queſtion his ſtrictneſs, whether it be ſincere: If his Senſe of Piety were real, it would be more laſting and uniform; and therefore without Breach of Charity, I think I may look on him in his greateſt Severity, rather to act a part on a Stage, and to ſerve a preſent Turn and Occaſion, than to be really in his mind what ſuch Strictneſs would repreſent him. And therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever true Devotion is in any of that Communion, ought to be aſcrib'd to ſomewhat elſe, than to the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Church: For even thoſe things which they are uſed to boaſt moſt of, which I have mentioned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, we ſhall eaſily find to have little that is truly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, much that is greatly faulty in them; and if their beſt things are no better, what are their worſt? If the Subject of their <hi>Glory is ſhameful,</hi> what will become of the reſt?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59271:7"/> 2. And therefore I'll now ſhew what we have juſtly to except againſt their fore-mentioned pretences to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for Monkery in general, which they boaſt ſo much of, calling it <hi>Status Perfectionis &amp; religioſus,</hi> as if beſides the State of Men in Holy Orders, that were a State of <hi>Perfection,</hi> and nothing elſe worthy the Name of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious.</hi> We confeſs, that ſcarcely as to any thing concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Externals of Religion, doth the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> diſtinguiſh it ſelf from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church ſo much, as that there is not any Proviſion made, or ſo much as a Suppoſition of ſuch Monaſteries, or religious Houſes, or publick places of Retirement for devout Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as they are called, being again ever ſetled among us. For tho' we are not ſo raſh as utterly to abhor and throw away every thing that at any time had been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Superſtition, yet we are very well contented that Monaſteries ſhould never be rebuilt among us. For we do not look on the Life of Monks as any great help to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, or an inſtance of true Religion prevailing where they are found; much leſs that they are neceſſary in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>For it is evident that the firſt and pureſt Ages of the Church did not know any thing of them: Almoſt three Centuries paſſed without any mention of them in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtory. <hi>Antony</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> in the Diocleſian Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, being taken notice of as the firſt of that Way. We read indeed of ſome that did lead a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſevere Courſe, and denied themſelves much of the (perhaps) lawful Pleaſures of this Life, in reſpect to Religion and the other Life; but theſe were not <hi>Monks,</hi> or the modern <hi>Aſceticks;</hi> tho' it hath been the way of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in more inſtances than this to impoſe ſome new thing on the World upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of ſome good and reverend Old Name: For
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59271:8"/>the Lives of the ancient <hi>Aſceticks,</hi> or mortified Men, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much from the preſent <hi>Monks</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> We find not that they engaged themſelves in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Vow, diſtinct from, or above that of their Baptiſm. For whatever their general Courſe of Life was, they would take the Liberty to break their Rule ſometimes in order to extraordinary Charity, or when an occaſion offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf of doing more good; as is recorded particularly concerning <hi>Spiridion</hi> a Biſhop in <hi>Cyprus.</hi> Nor do we find that they always continued in the ſame State of Life; but took ſuch a ſevere courſe on themſelves at ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular times, and on ſome ſpecial occaſions, (as the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarites</hi> of old did) to humble, and bring their Bodies under, and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth the married; but not to continue always ſo, leſt Satan ſhould tempt them; and they reckoned it in an higher degree praiſe-worthy for every Act of Mortification to be voluntary, than that they ſhould once for all force themſelves to it: And therefore ſtill retained a Power to themſelves, and did va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from this Method-ſometimes, and on occaoſin would indulge themſelves a greater, tho' ſtill a lawful Liberty. They took not on them the Vow of <hi>Poverty,</hi> nor pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Perfection in Beggery, but reckoned every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God to be good; and even the outward good things of this Life to be <hi>the Gift and Grace of God,</hi> if they be well employed, according to 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. and remembred that Saying of our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Acts</hi> 20, 35. <hi>It is more bleſſed to give than to receive.</hi> Nor did they vow what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now calls <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> but reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves as chaſte in Wedlock; and as for <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> the third part of the <hi>Monks</hi> Vow, they thought it ſufficient to obey the Commands of God, and knew not of any other Obedience due from them, but only to their Governours in Church and State, whoſe lawful Commands they reckoned themſelves obliged to, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59271:8"/>to the more regular Adminiſtration of Affairs, and the more peaceable Government of the World; much leſs had they any diſtinct Rules to be ſet up in Competition with the Laws of God, and urged as neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, making even the Commandments of God of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as many of the <hi>Monks</hi> Rules apparently do, as might be eaſily made to appear. Such religious Men as theſe, there were in the firſt Ages, who practiſed a ſtricter Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than others, that God's Name might be the more hallowed by them, the more it was profaned by the reſt of the World, and who were more than ordinary inſtant and conſtant in Prayers for a Bleſſing on the Church and State, of which they were Members; and by the Strictneſs and Severity of their Lives, made ſome amends for the Negligence and Viciouſneſs of the Age in which they lived.</p>
            <p>And many ſuch as theſe, we doubt not, are now among us, who yet utterly diſlike the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Mankery. And if by the Monaſtick Life all this were done, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe deſigned, it were juſtly to be commended: For let Men deny themſelves as much as they will, and uſe their Chriſtian Liberty to the Reſtraint of themſelves by a voluntary Self denial and Mortification, to keep their Bodies under, and thereby get a better Temper of Mind. But all this will not ſuffice in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For it is not enough for a man to live ſo ſtrict and holy a Life, unleſs he enter into a Vow particularly to this purpoſe. Nay, though a man do take on him all theſe Vows of <hi>Chaſtity, Poverty</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> and tho' they be made to his Biſhop or Confeſſor, who one would think were the propereſt perſons in the Caſe, yet ſtill it is not ſufficient; he cannot be ſaid to be in this <hi>religious State,</hi> unleſs he vow Obedience to another kind of Spiritual Juriſdiction. So that it is neither the living ſo ſtrictly, nor vowing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59271:9"/>to live ſtrictly, as the moſt ſevere <hi>Monks;</hi> but it is their being of a particular Order, and living under ſuch and ſuch Rule, that is ſo meritorious; ſo that by Monkery indeed, Monkery is encouraged, and ſome politick and Secular Deſigns anſwered; but the Advancement of Piety and Devotion is not principally deſigned or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. But to diſcourſe more diſtinctly of it;</p>
            <p>In a Monaſtick Life theſe three things are eſpecially remarkable,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſecluded, and perhaps Eremetical way of living which they lead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Conſtancy and Regularity of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons practiſed there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Severity of their Rules, and Auſterity of their Lives.</p>
            <p>But I muſt needs ſay, that there is little of true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, that I can diſcover in any of theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Their being ſhut up from the World, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Deſarts, is no very proper Inſtance of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, or agreeable to the Deſign of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>For a man ſhould converſe in the World, elſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo well underſtand it, what is amiſs, or wanting in it, nor how even to apply and place the Emphaſis of his Prayers.</p>
            <p>A man that lives in a Wilderneſs, or ſhut up always in a Monaſtery, it is poſſible that he may keep himſelf free from the Defilements of the World; but yet it muſt be looked on as much more noble and commendable to converſe in the World, and yet to avoid the Pollution of it.</p>
            <p>And tho' by ſuch a ſecluded Life he may eſcape one kind of Temptation, yet ſtill he will be at leaſt as liable to the two others, that ariſe from the <hi>Devil,</hi> or his own <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> as ever. And if he avoid ſome Sins, yet ſtill he will be more ſubject to others, Sowerneſs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59271:9"/>Moroſeneſs, Melancholly, Cenſoriouſneſs, ſpiritual Pride, and other Sins of as high a Nature as thoſe, which by being ſhut up from the World he pretends to avoid. And yet ſuch as theſe are generally legible and obſervable in the very Looks, Converſation and Carriage of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Hermits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed Retiredneſs ſometimes is an excellent help to the Mind, by giving it time to recollect it ſelf, and to reflect on its former Miſcarriages, and the better to prepare it ſelf for its future Encounters in the World. But a man may exceed in the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Degrees of this, as well as of other Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and lawful Enjoyments; and ſo it may become a Snare and an Evil to him: For the mind will naturally be as much tir'd with Solitude as with Bufineſs: Beſides, that the Devil is always moſt buſie when men are idle, and Diverſion and Recreation is as neceſſary to moſt Tempers, as Health and Cheerfulneſs are; and fits a man even for the Duties of Religion. For the keeping the Mind in a conſtant Bent, tho' of Devotion, will in a ſhort time weaken its Spring and dull its Edge; and the Acts of Devotion in ſuch a mind, will, it's to be feared, be rather a formal piece of Drudgery than a reaſonable Service. And though we ſhould grant, that by being confined to a Monaſtery, a man might better eſcape the Defilements of any kind of Sin; yet it muſt be granted, that he cannot be in ſo much capacity of doing good in the World as if he converſed freely with it: And <hi>Sozomon</hi> quotes it as a moſt remarkable Saying of ſome of the firſt Monks,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soc. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> That he that abſtains from Evil, but doth no Good, ought to be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a very bad Man; and ſo the Commands of Scripture enjoyn us to take Care to do Good, as well as to abſtain from Evil, elſe we ſhall be reckoned among the unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Servants. We are ſure that publick Service ought to be preferred before private, the Glory of God, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59271:10"/>the Good of Men being more advanced by it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though that man that lives in a Wilderneſs, and ſerves God there when he is forced to it by Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may hope for a Bleſſing, tho' he be alone, and neither worſhippeth God in Publick, nor gives a good Example to the World; yet he that runs into a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be wondred at and admired, and neglects the ordinary and moſt uſeful way of ſerving God, there is too much reaſon to fear <hi>he hath his Reward.</hi> At leaſt how far ſoever it may pleaſe God to pardon his blind Zeal, and want of Diſcretion, yet certainly this Example of his ought not to be recommended to all, as a Rule for them to walk by. The firſt Monks we grant, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and pious Men, and were compelled to forſake their Houſes, and live in Solitude; but it is very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to make their manner of Life a Pattern to be followed in the quiet and peaceable Ages of the Church. For this would be to ſhew our ſelves inſenſible of the goodneſs of God to us, in giving us the Liberty of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him freely and openly, and that we dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our Religion without fear of loſing our Lives. And for the ſame reaſon we ſhould ſtill chuſe to celebrate the Sacrament in an <hi>upper Room,</hi> becauſe our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and his Holy Apoſtles did ſo; and ſhould have our religious Aſſemblies in <hi>Crypts</hi> and Vaults under Ground, becauſe the firſt Chriſtians, in times of Difficulty and Perſecution, often durſt uſe no other.</p>
            <p>And as the Solitude of a Monaſtick Life is no proper Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtnce or Expreſſion of true Devotion, was not known in the firſt Ages of the Church, and afterwards was not taken up of Choice, but by Neceſſity: So alſo in the <hi>laſt</hi> place, I obſerve, that the Goſpel of Chriſt, and the Rules of Living, which are given us by himſelf, and his Holy Apoſtles, never enjoyn or ſuppoſe any ſuch thing. We are always ſuppoſed to live in Company and Society;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59271:10"/>and accorpingly the Precepts of our Saviour and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are adapted to the common Caſes of Men, and the Concerns of ſuch as converſe freely in the World. And therefore I muſt needs ſay, that it hath been very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordered, that there ſhould be new and diſtinct Rules made for thoſe that delight in this ſolitary and Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick way of Life: For they are ſuch a kind of men as the Goſpel of Chriſt hath no proper Rules for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> And I am afraid that there is as little true Devotion in their ſo frequent and conſtant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers enjoyned and practiſed in their Monaſteries, though this be confeſſedly what is moſt commendable in their way of Life, and is the only way by which they themſelves can pretend to do any Good in the World. (If I except thoſe, which are but very few, that workwith their Hands.)</p>
            <p>Praiſe and Prayer is therefore acceptable with God, as it is in the volunrary Expreſſion of our Souls, a Free-will Offering and Sacrifice which we offer to God, in conſideration of his infinite Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies and Perfections in himſelf, his former un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved Goodneſs to us, and our Liableneſs to him. Now the conſtant Prayers uſed in their Monaſteries, in more particulars than one, come ſhort of that true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion due from Men to their Maker: For firſt, they are as much as can be <hi>forced</hi> on a rational Being, and on that account muſt needs loſe much of their Worth and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptableneſs. The <hi>Monks</hi> are obliged by the Rules of their ſeveral Orders to ſay ſuch and ſuch Prayers, and juſt at ſuch and ſuch times, whatever Devotion or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Mind they have; and they are ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed if they fail of them. Exactly at Midnight, at two or three a Clock in the Morning, ſo very often, and at ſo very unſeaſonable times, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have confeſſed this ſtrictneſs of their <hi>Devotions,</hi> to be of all the greateſt Burden of their Lives;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59271:11"/>And yet this they muſt do in Imitation of ſome holy Man of Old, who is recorded to have pray'd at theſe Houres; whereas theſe Mens Devotions is not warm enough to keep them awake when they are at Prayer. And therefore theſe Prayers not being the free Emanations of their own mind, methinks the praiſe of them is not ſo much due to the <hi>Monks</hi> themſelves, as to the head and founder of their Order, who obliged them to ſuch Rules.</p>
            <p>And their Devotion is little more praiſe-worthy than that of the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Avignon,</hi> and ſeveral other Places, who are once in a Week forced to go to Church and hear a Sermou, (as theſe <hi>Monks</hi> are) at leaſt to ſit there whilſt a Sermon is preached, and return home as good Chriſtians as they went thither.</p>
            <p>But then they are not only thus ſtrictly obliged to ſuch Hours of Prayer, for that were ſomewhat tolerable, they might poſſibly be intent on their Prayers, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But they are at the ſame time taught, that they need only ſay the Words with their Mouths; it is not abſolutely neceſſary that their mind ſhould go along with them, and this together with the other muſt needs ſpoyl all true Devotion. The frequency and unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of their Prayers, will make it very difficult for them to attend as they ought, and their Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the No-neceſſity of attention at Prayers, will certainly make them to yield to theſe difficulties, and ſo there may be abundance of <hi>Words</hi> ſaid, but no <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> perform'd.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, they have a way of being eaſed of this trouble of the Prayers, for according to their Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, it is allowable for a man to get or hire another to ſay his Prayers for him. At leaſt he may be diſpenſed with by his Superiour, and this Diſpenſation is good, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be a juſt Reaſon or Occaſion for it or no, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59271:11"/>to an excellent Maxim of theirs, <hi>Non ad Valo rem, ſed ad Juſtitiam requiritur Cauſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if after all this, Men ſtill will be more than they need ſtrict in their Prayers, according to the Rules of their Orders, they almoſt conſtantly offend in the End, and Deſign of their Devotions. For they do them not ſo much to benefit the World, or work themſelves up to a better temper of Mind; But to perform a task im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them, and which they have vowed to perform, or eſpecially to merit by their works. For they do not ſo much as pretend that this ſtrictneſs in Devotion is abſolutely Neceſſary for their Salvation, (for elſe why do they not enjoyn it to all, ſeeing all have the ſame need of Salvation?) and therefore the ſole end of all this ſtrictneſs and conſtancy in Prayers, is only to get Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for others. Which Opinion, beſides that it will mightily diſcourage Men of an ordinary Charity, from being very intent on what they do, when they are ſenſible they Labour only for another; It coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanceth alſo a falſe and dangerous Doctrine concerning the Merit of good Works, and incourageth all vicious practiſes in other Men, who will hope to be ſaved, tho not by their own Prayers, yet by the Prayers of theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Monks</hi> ſaid for them.</p>
            <p>So that on many accounts, there is little of true Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be found in that conſtant courſe of Prayers, ſaid ſo regularly by the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Hermits;</hi> Not to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral other particulars, concerning the <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> of their Prayers, the <hi>Object</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped or prayed to, the <hi>Perſons prayed for,</hi> and the like, which I may have Occaſion to mention afterwards, which being put together, do abundantly ſhow the impropriety, and the worthleſsneſs of ſuch Devotions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And as to the <hi>Auſterities</hi> of the Lives of their <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Nuns,</hi> the Puniſhments which they inflict
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59271:12"/>on themſelves, as they profeſs for the ſake of Religion, by <hi>coarſe</hi> and <hi>uneaſie Garments, ſcanty Food and Fare, long and tedious Watchings, frequent and cruel Whippings, and Laſhings,</hi> and other ſuch Courſe and Harſh Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which they uſe towards their own Bodies. I confeſs I pity them, but can diſcern little or no true Chriſtian Devotion in them.</p>
            <p>For <hi>all Severity</hi> to our Bodies is not Devotion, or any part of that Self-denial which the Goſpel requires; nor is this of theirs, though they pretend it to be <hi>for the ſake of Religion;</hi> but their inſiſting ſo ſtrictly on it, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing themſelves ſo much on it, is of very <hi>bad Conſequence</hi> to Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Puniſhment</hi> which men inflict on themſelves is not Religion, nor commendable, nor is the patient bearing of it always a Sign of a true Chriſtian Temper. Chriſt hath no where told us, that he that can faſt longeſt, or endure moſt Laſhes is the beſt Man; but he that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf and his Life beſt. We have ſtrange Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Inſenſibleneſs of Pain in many of the worſt Principles and moſt profligate Conſciences: The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath his Martyrs as well as God; and if the volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inflicting Puniſhment on themſelves be a Sign of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. muſt have been a very devout Generation of Men. Therefore it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny religious Commendation of a Man, that he can ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whip, or laſh himſelf, or bear it from another without flinching: Such a man might have made a good <hi>Gladia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> but ſeems not ſo well qualified for a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is all Puniſhment which Men inflict on themſelves, and ſay they do it for the <hi>ſake of God and Religion,</hi> always a Sign of true Devotion: For in other Caſes, it is not Men's Saying that they deſign well, which will make their Actions acceptable with God; but it is their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he hath commanded, and for the ends which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59271:12"/>he deſigned and intended, with which he is well pleaſed. And it too often happens, that men do Actions having a ſhow of Sanctity, and of great Self-denial, which yet are received by God only, with a <hi>who hath required this at your hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Self-denial indeed is commanded in Scripture, and is neceſſary alſo to many and excellent Purpoſes, to ſubdue a man's Paſſions and Affections, and to bring him to a right underſtanding of himſelf; to put a man in mind of leaving the pleaſant things of this World, ſenſibly to affect him with the Condition of thoſe that are in Miſery and always want them, and to inure him to bear patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the adverſe things, or whatever it ſhall pleaſe God to lay upon him. It is neceſſary that a man ſhould have a mind always ready and prepared to loſe all for Chriſt; and therefore he ought often to deny himſelf ſomewhat for the Sake of Chriſt, that he may give full proof to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that his mind is affected as it ought to be: And by voluntary Acts of this Nature he preſerves a Power over himſelf, and is much the more fitted for all the Accidents of Life, and for the Exerciſe of Devotion.</p>
            <p>But let a man have a care that he keep within due Bounds: He may exceed and tranſgreſs both in the <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and in the <hi>End and Deſign</hi> of ſuch Mortification. He exceeds in the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of it, when he inflicts ſuch Severity on himſelf as ſhall render him unfit for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and uſeleſs in his Place. God delights not in the Puniſhment of his Creatures, but deſires their Good here as far as it is conſiſtent with their greater Good hereafter. And though he requires Self-denial of us, it is only in ſuch a meaſure as is for our Good, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the bettering of our Temper, and to cut off the Occaſions of Sin in us. And therefore it is a great fault in any man on this pretence to render his Life ſo unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to himſelf, as that he ſhall not be able to ſerve God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59271:13"/>contentedly, cheerfully, and without Diſtraction: As a Man may be to blame alſo for his Charity, when with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a juſt Occaſion he throws, or gives away all; For if this Courſe were allowed or followed, the worſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they that know leaſt how to uſe an Eſtate well, would be the richeſt and Owners of all, and the only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Authority and Power.</p>
            <p>And he tranſgreſſeth alſo in the <hi>End and Deſign</hi> of ſuch Severity, when he pretends to merit by it, and hopes to buy Heaven (which is the Gift of God) with a few Laſhes, or a little Money.</p>
            <p>And I have too much reaſon to undervalue and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Severity of the <hi>Monks</hi> on both theſe Accounts. They <hi>often</hi> tie themſelves up to ſuch Degrees of Strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as are above the Meaſures of a man, and conſequently not to the purpoſe of Religion and Devotion. And they <hi>always</hi> deſign to purchaſe Heaven for themſelves or other, by the Merits of ſuch Sufferings: At the ſame time undervaluing the Sufferings of Chriſt, and over-valuing their own; and yet making them of leſs worth in God's Eſteem than elſe they would be, by their own ſetting ſo high a price upon them.</p>
            <p>And beſides all this, their inſiſting ſo ſtrictly on theſe pieces of Auſterity, and placing ſuch Religion and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in them, is of very ill Conſequence to other purpoſes.</p>
            <p>It makes men to acquieſce in the <hi>means</hi> as the <hi>end,</hi> to content themſelves with having performed their Faſts, their Number of Prayers and Laſhes, without ever aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at any Reformation and Change of Temper and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes; than which nothing can be more abſurd in it ſelf, or more contrary to the Deſign of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>It makes men alſo to eſteem this or that kind of Meat and Drinke, Condition or Courſe of Life, to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or ſinful, which really is not; which doth much harm, even to Religion: For it diſparageth God's Creation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59271:13"/>and brings an <hi>evil Report</hi> upon the Land. It neceſſarily makes Men querulous and cenſorious; and is the very thing which our Saviour took ſuch pains to correct, and did ſo often rebuke the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of his Time for.</p>
            <p>And this extraordinary pretence to Severity, brings the Perſons of ſuch Men into Eſteem, whatever their Principles, Opinions and Practices otherwiſe are, and ſo injures Religion. For ſo <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Hiſtory tells us, That thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> that have moſt hurt the Church, were ſuch kind of pretended mortified Men, as <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Pelugins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So that what do theſe more than others? Do not even the Publicans ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore however praiſe-worthy the <hi>Monaſtick</hi> Life may have been formerly, and what ever good may have been done, by ſome of that Order: Yet this is no Plea for the <hi>Monks</hi> at this time. For the <hi>Ancients</hi> were very Inſtrumental in converting many to Chriſtianity; but <hi>theſe</hi> only live on the ſpoil of Chriſtians already made ſo. And conſidering the preſent poſture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in the World, this <hi>Monkiſh</hi> way of living is very improper, and the abuſes that are made of it in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are plainly intollerable. Where Men are taught to place Religion in a certain Way and Trade of Life, rather than in a truly Chriſtian Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. It ſtrikes at the very Foundation of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for Men to be made to believe, that the living or dying in the Habit of this or that ſevere Order of <hi>Monks,</hi> will have an Influence on the Soul, and give it a better Title to Heaven. And yet it is too notorious that theſe things are conſidently taught and believed among them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, let Men deny themſelves as much as they will, for the ſake of God and of Religion, to humble themſelves for their Sins, and to keep their Bodies and Paſſions under. Let them uſe their Chriſtian Liberty to the reſtraint of themſelves, by a voluntary ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59271:14"/>as far as they find it neceſſary or expedient; But for this to be brought into a trade, is the moſt prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous thing in the World. Eſpecially, let them have a Care of cenſuring and judging others, who tread not exactly in their Steps, or of over-valuing themſelves, on account of this ſevere and ſtrict courſe of Life. For it is evident that for the moſt part it is not Religion brings them thither, or any extraordinary love of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; but their Parents ſend them thither as a pretty cheap way of providing for their younger Children, that ſo they may be able the more honourably to diſpoſe of the reſt agreeably to the Grandeur of the Family. Therefore if they will commend the Inſtitution of Monaſteries, as a good and frugal way of breeding up of Youth, or of providing for a ſpare Child or two, let them do what they will. But it is not to be ſuffered, that when they ſerve eſpecially, or only to ſuch Politick ends; yet that they ſhould be boaſted of as the beſt, or only Chriſtian and Religious way of Life, as if the Perſons in them were the only <hi>Religious,</hi> and all others were <hi>ſecular,</hi> and in ſome Meaſure <hi>Profane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides it is very <hi>unreaſonable</hi> for Perſons to be ſhut up in Monaſteries, ſo as they are, when they are young, and before they can have fully conſidered what Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations they may have, or how they ſhall be able to bear and withſtand them; and yet if they have but once, though of a ſudden, through their own Melancholly, or the Inſinuation of others, take the vow on themſelves, there is ordinarily no revoking or drawing back for ever.</p>
            <p>It is very <hi>cruel</hi> alſo for Perſons to be put there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Conſideration of their ſeveral Tempers, and Circumſtances. For inſtead of benefiting the Publick, which they pretend, it robbeth the World of many an one that would have been uſeful to it in an Active Life and Station. And ſome by their Tempers do not need
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59271:14"/>ſuch Mortification, as the melancholly and dejected. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot bear the Strictneſs and Confinement, the weak and ſickly. And now to force this ſame courſe of Life on all, or ſuch a number of Men, indifferently, is like the Cruelty of that Tyrant that would make all men of the ſame length: And the beſt that can be ſaid in the caſe, is, that the Perſons who thus confine and ſhut up their Children and Relations, are like to the Perſecutors, who in the like manner ſhut up St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was Cruelty in them, tho by ſo doing, they gave him a greater Opportunity for private Devotion. So that in truth I look on the Monaſteries, as they are now ordered, to be rather a kind of Priſons, and places of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, than convenient places of Retirement in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the freer and more undiſturbed Exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Devotion. And if I am not miſtaken, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf, whatever ſhe pretends, really thinks ſo of them: For the worſt Puniſhment that ſhe inflicts on a Prieſt for one of the worſt of Offences, <hi>viz.</hi> for his violating the Seat of Confeſſion, is, that he ſhall be condemned to be ſhut up in a Monaſtery; and I dare ſay, that he and I agree in thinking that to be a ſevere Puniſhment, rather than an Help to Devotion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> And if the Multitude of Monaſteries in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no certain Sign of Devotion flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among them, they have little reaſon to boaſt of their <hi>works of Charity:</hi> For it is moſt plain, that the biggeſt part of their Charity is turned this way, to the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and endowing Monaſteries, and to the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Monaſtick way of living.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, though I am very loth to find fault with any pretence to Charity, yet I have too much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon on many accounts to think very meanly of all that which is practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath been given to that Church under the Name of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59271:15"/>
               <hi>Charity,</hi> and is now enjoyed by it, hath for the moſt part been ill gotten, and is as ill employed.</p>
            <p>And here I will not treat of the temporal Power of the Pope himſelf, and of the ſeveral Principalities which he ſtands poſſeſſed of in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ranged under the Head of <hi>Charity,</hi> according to my acception of the Word; though it might be eaſily made to appear, that they have generally been gotten by unjuſt and unlawful, or at beſt by harſh and cruel Means, and ſuch as one would not expect from the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> But I concern my ſelf with ſmaller and more private Benefactions and Gifts, though theſe are ſo conſiderable, that generally a third part, often half the Lands of a Country are the Propriety of the Church, Now all this is gotten chiefly from men that are dying, who can keep their Riches no longer, and therefore who do not ſo much give this from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as from their Heirs; and is eſpecially, as it were, to buy Heaven; and a man muſt have a moſt deſpicable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of Heaven, who will not give all the good things of this Life, when he can no longer uſe or enjoy them, for the Purchaſe of it: And what is given from ſo bad a Principle, is commonly applied to as bad a purpoſe. It is a common Obſervation, that in all the Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys the Poor are the moſt miſerable in the World; and their Secular Prieſts too are generally in a ſad Condition, notwithſtanding the infinite Riches of that Church: And ſo the Regulars only have any conſiderable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by them; and they alſo, as it were, club together to ſet up one great Man as Cardinal, or Head of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in mighty Pomp and State; and heap Riches and Preferments on him till he can hardly bear them. So that one can ſcarcely ſuppoſe ſo great Riches as that Church is in common endowed with, to be gotten into fewer Hands, or do leſs Good than it doth amongſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59271:15"/>them. Let them not therefore boaſt of their <hi>Charity,</hi> whilſt amidſt ſo great Plenty, they ſuffer the Poor to want ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly; and yet to make a Show build a fine Hoſpital in two or three of their chief Towns: For perhaps no where in the World do the Rich more exalt themſelves, and tyrannize over the Poor, no where is there a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inequality of Conditions; no where is there ſo much given to the Church and Charity, and no where is the Eſtate of the Church engroſſed into ſo few Hands, to maintain Grandeur, rather than to be a Relief to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty. For the Cardinals above Seventy in number are maintained out of the Church-Revenues, and yet are by their Creation equal to Kings, and ſuperior to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Now if this be Charity to have a prodigious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue for the Maintenance of the Church and Poor, and yet to employ this to the Luxury of a few, and to let the reſt periſh, I will acknowledge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the moſt charitable Church in the World. And if it be ſaid that a great deal indeed hath been given to good and truly charitable uſes, but is now perhaps miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>employed: I anſwer, it is poſſible it may be ſo, yet ſtill I have ſome reaſon to queſtion it; For their Doctrines of Merit, and of buying Souls out of Purgatory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are enough to ſpoil their works of Charity, and make them to be rather eſteem'd a Bargain of Sale than a free Gift. And yet their Donations run commonly in this Form, <hi>I give this to ſuch a Monaſtery for the good of my Soul, or of the Souls of other perſons deceaſed, or for the Honour of ſuch a Saint;</hi> but ſeldom for the good of the Poor, the Maintenance and Support of true Piety and Religion; or for the Glory and Honour of God: And yet in my Opinion ſuch as theſe are the only ends for which a Gift ought to be eſteemed <hi>charitable,</hi> or will be accepted by God as ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59271:16"/>
            <p> But now on the other ſide, though the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> own not either <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or any other of their Pick-pocket Doctrines, yet <hi>Charity</hi> urged by us from tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian Principles, hath had more force, and done more good than all their Tricks and Devices put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For ſo Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> hath in part ſhewn, and it might be more fully demonſtrated, that in theſe laſt 120, or 130 Years, ſince the ſettling of the Reformation among us, there hath been more and greater <hi>Churches, Schools</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> built and endowed, better Proviſion made for the Poor; more and better care taken, not only for the Maintenance, but eſpecially for the Inſtruction of the ignorant and meaner ſort of People; In ſhort, all parts of <hi>Charity</hi> more fully exerciſed, than can be ſhewn in any the like number of Years ſince Chriſtianity came into this Countrey. Indeed the general Strain of our Peoples <hi>Charity</hi> runs to the doing of more good, and is more properly expreſſed than theirs is. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> build Monaſteries, in which Proviſion is made for a few people to live in Idleneſs and Luxury under pretence of Devotion and Retirement: Ours relieve the Sick and Needy (tho not Regulars) and think it better Charity to preſerve a poor Family from ſtarving (of which ſo many thouſands die in Popiſh Countreys) than to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an idle <hi>Monk</hi> or <hi>Nun,</hi> or to make a Preſent to the Lady at <hi>Loretto,</hi> or offer Candles and Tapers to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or Saint of the Town in which we live. We, by ſo beſtowing our <hi>Charity,</hi> both <hi>honour God,</hi> and <hi>do good to Men.</hi> They do neither, but do Homage to a Saint that neither knows them, nor receives any Good by the Honour which they give them.</p>
            <p>It is indeed confeſſed, that our Churches are not ſo adorned as they ought ſometimes: But that is no Fault of our Church, but of the Iniquity of the Times, and of thoſe Diſſentions which they raiſe among us; but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59271:16"/>they are decently grave, and as well ſitted to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt a devout mind without Diſtraction as can be. We love to have our Churches neat and handſom, to ſhew we do not grudge whatever may be required to make them in ſome meaſure a fit place for Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but we ſee not any neceſſity of having them ſo ſplendidly rich and fine; we think it would rather di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert mens minds from the Buſineſs of the Place, than aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them in the Duties of it.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, in no part of <hi>Charity</hi> can they pretend to exceed us, conſidering our Circumſtances, unleſs it be in that of Prayer for the Dead, when they hire ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Maſſes to be ſaid for them; but we think not this ſo much <hi>Charity</hi> to the perſon deceaſed, as to the Prieſt; for he doubtleſs receives moſt Benefit from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And whatever they pretend, the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Saints canonized and commemorated among them, is neither a Sign of their good State and Condition of their Church, nor is their keeping ſo many Holydays in remembrance of them any inſtance of true Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>As for many of the Saints which they commemorate we own as well as they, and can pretend as good a right in them as they can, becauſe we own, and will ſubmit to whatever can be urged from them; ſuch are the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts; and after them alſo the Biſhops, Martyrs and Confeſſors in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church: But we confeſs that we have not the ſame eſteem of many whom they commemorate as Saints, and utterly diſallow of their Canonizing or Sainting of them: For many of them (I believe) never had any Being, but in the Fancy of theſe Saint-makers, who yet are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorated, and prayed to as well as any others. Such are St. <hi>Longinus,</hi> under which name they have made a Man of the Spear which pierced our Saviour's Bleſſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59271:17"/>Body. St. <hi>Almachius,</hi> on <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. which only comes from the Corruption of <hi>Almanack;</hi> St. <hi>Amphibalus,</hi> who was only St. <hi>Alban</hi>'s Cloak; St. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula,</hi> and her 11000 Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, of whom no Foot-ſteps can be found in true Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. Many of them, I fear, it had been better that they had never been, as being notoriouſly vicious and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in their Lives. And others, though more inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, yet if we believe what is written in their Lives, were ſo prodigiouſly ridiculous, that a wiſe and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man would be aſham'd of ſuch Company. To hear Men in an Extaſie of Devotion to talk Nonſence, or to preach to Birds and Beaſts, to run naked, to wander vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily in Deſarts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is more likely with ſober men, to bring their Perſons and Actions into Contempt and Scorn, than to affect them with any quick Senſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; at beſt it will excite Men only to that extatical and enthuſiaſtical kind of Devotion, which was in vogue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathens, whoſe Prieſts were beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they ſpake in the Name of their Gods; and their moſt celebrated Exerciſes of Religion were ſuch kind of irrational Actions; but there is nothing of this at all countenanced under Chriſtianity: For the Goſpel would make us wiſe as well as devout; and it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that we put off the Man, but the Old Man and its Vices when we become Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And though we are ſenſible of many among us that have been very exemplary for Vertue and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and have no reaſon to doubt of their Salvation; but have as full Aſſurance of it, at leaſt, as they have of their Saints; yet we are very ſhy of canonizing or ſaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, becauſe we know not Mens Hearts, nor dare we to preſume to diſpoſe ſo abſolutely of Heaven as the Pope doth. We thank God for thoſe that have lived and died well among us, and exhort our people to imitate all the Good which ſhewed it ſelf in them;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59271:17"/>but we know not to what purpoſe Canonization is. If it be only to recommend their Vertues to Example, the Canonization of them will ſignifie no more than the bare Hiſtory of their good Lives faithfully recorded would do; but if it be in order to praying to them we utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it. And it is too plain, that this is the end of their being canonized: For from that time ſolemn Prayer and Invocation is allowed and offered up to them. And this I believe hath been an occaſion of their falling from the Truth of Chriſtian Doctrine as well as Practiſe: For they taking ſuch a man to be a Saint, think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to follow and vindicate whatever he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did or ſaid, as holy and true, not conſidering that the beſt of meer Men have been guilty of Miſtakes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections; and then much more may we ſuſpect the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Underſtanding, the Vertue and Piety of many of thoſe that fill up the bigger part of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Kalendar.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon we think there is not much Religion or Devotion expreſſed in the keeping up the Memory of ſuch Saints, by ſo many Holydays obſerved among them.</p>
            <p>If they commend their Holydays for the opportunities afforded in them of ſerving God in publick, we have ſuch Conveniencies in many places every day.</p>
            <p>If they commend them as days ſet apart to Reſt and Idleneſs, we are not altogether of their mind; for we think we have as many as our Poor can well ſpare; and are ſure that they have more Holydays than their Poor can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to obſerve. So that their Holydays are no Advantage to any. The Rich need them not; becauſe if they have Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they may be idle and luxurious every day: But they are a great Evil and Burthen to the Poor, when they are forced to loſe ſo many days from their Work, by which they ſhould maintain themſelves and their Families. And though the Popes, by reaſon of this Cry of the Poor, have been
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59271:18"/>prevailed with to cut off many of thoſe days of Idleneſs, yet ſtill in moſt places the Number of them is intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As for Images, I ſhould have thought it more proper to range them among the <hi>Hinderances</hi> of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did I not ſee the Men of <hi>Rome</hi> to plead earneſtly for them, as <hi>Helps</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtances,</hi> and to blame us for not uſing them, and paying no reſpect to them.</p>
            <p>I confeſs my ſelf not acute enough to diſcern how they can any ways advance Devotion: For their paying ſuch Honour and Reſpect to them <hi>as they do own</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, muſt needs be a great Diſtraction, it diverting the Mind, and making Men ſpend their religious Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence on that which is expoſed to their View: but their paying ſuch Worſhip to them as <hi>they do pay, but are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to own,</hi> is flatly deſtructive to all true Devotion.</p>
            <p>They indeed plead the Ignorance of the People for the neceſſity of Images, and call them the Books of the Unlearned: But they muſt <hi>firſt</hi> ſuppoſe their People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferably ignorant to need ſuch Helps as theſe are. And to give the Prieſts their due, if any Ignorance would ſuffice to juſtifie ſuch a Practiſe, they take care to heep their People in Ignorance ſufficient: And <hi>then</hi> if they are ſo ignorant that they cannot worſhip God without an Image, the Church cannot be ſecure, but theſe ſo ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly People may worſhip the Image for God or Chriſt; or at leaſt as having ſome extraordinary Vertue in it, and ſo make an Idol of it, eſpecially when they ſee the Eyes and Hands of the Image to move, and ſee Miracles wrought by the Touch of it, as is frequently pretended and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be done: So that either there is no need of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, or great danger in the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, I am not of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Mind, who thinks that they may be properly or ſafely uſed to excite De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; at leaſt I muſt confeſs my ſelf of a different tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59271:18"/>from him. Methinks I repreſent God in greater Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to my ſelf, when I conſider him in his Works of Creation and Providence, than to ſee him pictured, as in the Clouds, though with Thunder in his Hand. And my Saviour appears more lovely to my mind and thoughts when I conſider him as coming into the World and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us, than when I ſee him pictured and carved on a Crucifix. For it is more uſeful to ſee him with the Eye of Faith than of Senſe, and it is not the Proportion of his Body repreſented to my Eyes, but the Dignity of his Nature, the Love that he bore me, and the Paſſions of his Soul for me, that I admire moſt, and which no Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil can draw.</p>
            <p>Beſides, a Picture or Image tells me nothing but what I knew before; and it is by what I knew before that I can make ſenſe or any devout uſe of this Picture; for elſe I might take it for another profane and idle Story. And I would fain know whether the reading conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately the 26, and 27th. Chapters of S. <hi>Matthew</hi> will not affect any pious Heart much more than the ſeeing and contemplating a Picture. Certainly if this will affect the Senſe and bodily Paſſions, the other will more work on our Reaſon, and that will be to better purpoſe. Nay, the ſeeing of any Picture often will naturally make it <hi>familiar,</hi> and not at all affecting to us.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And if the ſeverity of the <hi>Monks</hi> to their Bodies is not any great Sign of <hi>Devotion,</hi> much leſs can the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities uſed by the common People turn to any great Commendation of the Church. It is true, they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to keep Faſts, but it would make a Man laugh to read how their Caſuiſts have defined concerning the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> the Meaſure and End of Faſting. <hi>Eſcobar</hi> hath reſolved it, <q>That no Drink breaks a Faſt, be it Wine or Chocolat; and becauſe it is not wholeſom to drink without eating, you may eat two Ounces of Bread:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59271:19"/>For that is but a quarter of a Meal; and if a man ſhould chance to break his Vow of Faſting thus, he is not bound to faſt another day for it, unleſs on a new Obligation: And if all this be too hard, you may be diſpenſed with for your whole Life, and that whether there be any juſt cauſe for it or no. Nay, Servants, tho they eat ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo gluttonouſly of the Scraps, they break no Faſt.</q> Indeed there need be no Rules ſet down concerning the Poor Peoples obſerving Faſting Days: They are kept low enough without them: And as for the Rich, their Faſting is Mock-faſting, to faſt to Luxury, with Wine, and Fiſh, and Sweet-meats. Is not this great Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial? If any therefore are ſtill truly mortified, when they can thus help it, I muſt rather commend their own Piety, and devout Temper, than the Rules and Orders of their Church, which give ſo much Liberty, that a man muſt have a very croſs-grain'd Appetite, or be in the higheſt degree ſenſual, not to be willing to comply with it. We find then no Fault with Faſting being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd, and at ſet Seaſons: For we our ſelves commend and practiſe it; but let it not be to play tricks, but for true and real Mortification, and for the proper Ends of Mortification, to humble the Body to the Soul, and to bring the Mind to a better Temper; and to theſe ends is Faſting commanded by our Church; but not as if we looked on this or that kind of Meat to be unholy, or deſign'd to purchaſe Heaven by our Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as for their Pilgrimages, and Worſhip of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, they muſt needs have leſs pretence to Religion: For their Faſts, and other Auſterities ſomewhat reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble true Chriſtian Duties; but theſe have no Show that way. If Pilgrimage <hi>be enjoyn'd for Penance,</hi> then there is no Thanks due to the Perſon performing it.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59271:19"/>
            <p> If it be <hi>voluntary,</hi> there is no true Devotion in it: For the Worth of it muſt conſiſt in ſome of theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>viz.</hi> either, Firſt, That <hi>God</hi> is more preſent, or Secondly, more propitious in one publick place of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip than another: both which are contrary either to the Nature of God, or his Declaration in Scripture, when he ſays, <hi>In every place a pure Offering ſhall be offered to him,</hi> Mal. 1.11. And <hi>Where ever two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſts Name, he is in the midſt of them:</hi> Matt. 18.20. And the teaching otherwiſe is in ſome meaſure to revive <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> which allowed God, as to ſome caſes, to be ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed acceptably only in one place; or Thirdly, That the <hi>Saint</hi> is more preſent or propitious here than any where elſe: But we are ſpeaking of Devotion to God, not to the Saint; or Fourthly, That it is their <hi>puniſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> that is ſo acceptable; but that hath been ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcarded already: Or, Fifthly, That going ſo far, and taking ſuch pains <hi>is a Sign of their Love:</hi> But a man may ſhew his Love to God, and to his Saint too by more proper Inſtances, and do more good by it, which God, to be ſure, will better accept, and the Saint, if he be a Saint, will like as well. And therefore the making ſuch account of Pilgrimages, ſeems rather to favour the <hi>Mahometan,</hi> than the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion: For the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecca,</hi> is one of the five indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable points of the Mahometan Superſtition.</p>
            <p>And as For the <hi>Veneration of Reliques,</hi> all the World knows, what a Cheat is put on Men, in vending any old rotten Bone, or piece of Cloth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for a Relique of this or that Saint: So that according to a moderate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, I ſuppoſe ſcarcely one in a hundred is true: And ſome have pleaded they need not be true. Now whatever Devotion is performed <hi>to,</hi> or <hi>on occaſion</hi> of theſe Reliques, can be commendable only in regard of the Mind and devout Temper of the Perſon; which I think
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59271:20"/>might as acceptably ſhew it ſelf in any other proper time and place: And there is required a long <hi>Series</hi> of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences before the Sight of St. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Axe, or any ſuch other of their Reliques, can be pretended to raiſe a man's Devotion. But it being the chief Trade at <hi>Rome</hi> to ſell feigned pieces of Antiquity, and other ſuch worthleſs Trinkets at a high rate, I the leſs wonder, that they have ſuch an Eſteem for Reliques; for it is for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to keep up the Value of them, they being the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Commodities of the place.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And the Belief which they have of the <hi>Saints hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them,</hi> and their Practiſe of <hi>praying to them,</hi> is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Encouragement or Inſtance of true Devotion: For all <hi>Devotion</hi> is properly towards God; and therefore the making Addreſſes to any other cannot poſſibly have any direct Tendency to exalt our Devotion to him, but is really a great hindrance: For it takes mens Minds off from God, and ſets them on his Creature: And the ſame time that is ſpent in Prayer to them, ſurely is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpent in praying to God, who is more preſent with us, hears us better, and loves us more. And Men's go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints when God is preſent, naturally tends to provoke God's <hi>Jealouſie:</hi> For he declares himſelf <hi>jealous</hi> as to his Worſhip particularly, to ſet them up in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with God, and to create in Men an Opinion, that they are more eaſily entreated, and readier to do us a Kindneſs than he is. And therefore though Men may <hi>fear</hi> God more, yet they will rather love the Saint; and Love is the trueſt Motive to ſuch Devotion, as will be beſt accepted with God. And yet in this plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts all that Court which they make to the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that ſhe would <hi>pacifie the Anger</hi> of God the Father, or of the Son towards Men; they are repreſented ſevere, and almoſt cruel, to render her more amiable to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in her interceding for them: So they frequently in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59271:20"/>their printed allowed Books of Devotion, call her <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Mercy, and Pity,</hi> and other Names of the like Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. Now all the aſſurance they have of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo tender and compaſſionate, is only becauſe ſhe is a Woman; but they are aſſured of God's Mercy, both from his Nature and his Word: They have no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that ſhe, or any other Saint hears them; nor can they ſhew how the Saint can be rationally ſuppoſed to know every thing that we do or ſay; but they are well aſſured that God hears them: For he is ſtiled <hi>The God that heareth Prayer;</hi> which Prerogative of his, by every Prayer to a <hi>Saint,</hi> they may at leaſt ſuſpect that they intrench on. They are not aſſured that the Saint can help them; but they may be fully ſatisfied of his Help, who is Almighty. They have no Encouragement from Scripture for praying to Saints: For though the Angels rejoyce at the <hi>Repentance of a Sinner,</hi> it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that therefore every concern of Men is known, or Prayer heard by them; much leſs that we may pray to them for the Gift of Repentance, or any other Grace. And Prayer being ſo conſiderable a part of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we need not doubt but the Angels and Saints would refuſe it: For ſo St. <hi>John</hi> was rebuked for offering to worſhip the Angel, though ſuppoſed immediately and viſibly with him, <hi>Worſhip God,</hi> Rev. 19.20.</p>
            <p>So that if they prayed to Saints and Angels only to <hi>mediate and intercede</hi> for them to God, it is more than they have any Warrant or Allowance for. Chriſt being always repreſented as the Mediator between God and man; and the ſetting up his Servants in his Office, is as far as is poſſible a depoſing of him. Nor is it in this caſe, as it is in Courts on Earth (which is their common Excuſe) where a Favourite is made uſe of to repreſent our Cauſe and our Requeſt to the King: For this is done becauſe our Kings do not know our Perſons, nor underſtand our Caſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59271:21"/>nor can they be preſent in all places, and hear all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes themſelves: So that it is often neceſſary that Princes ſhould employ and truſt other than their own Eyes and Ears. Many things they think below them to enquire par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly into; and ſometimes they will do that at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of a Favorite, which they would not do for the ſake of a Perſon that is not particularly known to them. But there is no Room nor Occaſion for this in the Court of Heaven: For God is not only intimately known, but is immediately preſent to all his Creatures; as he hath declar'd himſelf no Reſpecter of Perſons, but to love all, and therefore there is no need of any Interceſſor for us, except the Lord Jeſus; he affects not empty Pomp and State; but his Providence extends to every particular Concern of the meaneſt of all his Creatures; and though he may give ſome undeſerved Favours, as longer Lives, and further Opportunities of Amendment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the ſake of others Prayers, yet no Man is ſo far his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, as to be able to perſwade him to reverſe his own Laws, and to ſave a wicked Perſon that continues in his Wickedneſs. On all which Accounts there is no Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of praying to the Saints ſo much as to <hi>intercede</hi> for us, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretends. But to pray to them to <hi>bleſs us,</hi> and <hi>give us</hi> this or that Temporal or Spiritual Good, as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> practiſe, and to ſuppoſe them to have Power to help us in this or that particular Difficulty and Diſtemper is plainly intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable: For this is in a great meaſure to revive Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, by which Men worſhipped this or that God for this or that particular Caſe. They muſt grant the Saint to have, though not an Original, yet a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and derivative Power, according to which he will not fail to aſſiſt them that worſhip him; and in all ſuch Prayer, methinks they even terminate their Worſhip on the Saint: For if I pray to a Saint to help me in this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59271:21"/>or that Difficulty, with a full aſſurance that this Saint hath ſufficient Power to help me, though I ſhould grant that this Saint received this Power from God, yet my Prayers terminate on the Saint. Indeed the Saint is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to God for that Power; but I ſeem to own my ſelf only obliged to the Saint, for his applying this his general Power to my particular Caſe: Juſt as I am ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to a man for giving me an Eſtate, though he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to the Government and Laws, that either he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed that Eſtate himſelf, or was empowered to give it to another.</p>
            <p>Beſides that they often pray to Saints for ſuch things, which, if they be only Creatures, they can have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to give, or to be even ſo much as the Inſtruments of conveying to us; and yet it is notorious, they pray ſometimes to the Saints for <hi>Grace,</hi> for <hi>Pardon of Sins,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> againſt them. So in <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>'s <hi>Pfalter,</hi> tranſlated into <hi>Italian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salmi di S. Bonav. in Lode della Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, per Giovan. Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſta Pinello. In Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa, Anno 1606.</note> and publiſhed for the uſe of the people, tho the Tranſlator and Publiſher ſays, that he had purged it from the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies which were in the former E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; yet we find ſuch paſſages as theſe to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> Pſal. 7. <hi>Come to her all ye that are heavy laden, and ſhe ſhall give Reſt and Refreſhment to your Souls.</hi> Pſal. 40. <hi>Cleanſe my Heart.</hi> Pſal. 41. <hi>Thou art the beginning and the end of my Salvation.</hi> Pſal. 44. <hi>By thy Holineſs my ſins are purged, and by thy Integrity, Incorruptibility is given to me.</hi> Pſal. 104. <hi>Eternal Salvation is in thy Hand, O Lady, and he that worthily honoueth thee ſhall obtain it;</hi> and many more Sayings of this nature, or worſe, if poſſible. Now can any man ſay, that ſuch Prayers as theſe are fit to be offered up to a Creature, or that they are Inſtances of the Devotion of a Chriſtian, when they are ſo offered? I am ſure that we charge the Heathen with giving Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59271:22"/>Worſhip to <hi>Men,</hi> though we can hardly find any Expreſſions or Prayers to their Gods, which are ſo high, and argue their terminating their Worſhip on them ſo fully as theſe, and other ſuch, which are commonly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thoſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to Saints, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. And whatever they pretend, the conſtant Trade which they make of <hi>Confeſſions and Penances,</hi> and their Doctrine concerning them, is ſo far from encouraging Devotion, that it is enough to remove all true Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the World, if the Providence of God did not miraculouſly interpoſe.</p>
            <p>For though they be very conſtant in their Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all their Sins to a Prieſt, yet the frequency of it in themſelves and others, makes them not ſo much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of themſelves; and though they may be more afraid of angring their Prieſts, yet they have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to abhor themſelves, or their Sins in the Sight of God any more for it.</p>
            <p>And when they have thus confeſſed, their Confeſſor may enjoyn what Penance he pleaſeth, or elſe may leave it to the Penitent's own Choice, as <hi>Eſcobar</hi> from <hi>Suarez.</hi> affirms; and men are not uſed to be very cruel to their own Bodies, or lay a very ſevere Penance on themſelves, when a lighter will ſerve: Or elſe the Confeſſor may ſay thus, <q>I impoſe on thee for Penance whatever good thing thou haſt done, or ſhalt do this Day, or this Week, or whatever Evil thou haſt, or ſhalt ſuffer.</q> And Cardinal <hi>Tolet</hi> is of the ſame mind too. Now will not this make a man mightily afraid of ſinning any more, when his ordinary courſe of Converſation, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Caſualties of Life ſhall be turned into a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Penance, Satisfaction, and Puniſhment for his Sin? And if the Confeſſor enjoyn no Penance at all, indeed he is to blame, ſays <hi>Eſcobar;</hi> but ſtill it is a Sacrament
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59271:22"/>for all that, becauſe a ſatisfactory penance is not an <hi>eſſential</hi> part of the Sacrament, but an <hi>Integral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if after all this the Confeſſor will impoſe a Penance, the Penitent may perform what he will of it: For, ſays <hi>Tolet,</hi> if he doth not perform his Penance, his Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtands good, only when he comes to Confeſſion next, he muſt confeſs that he did not perform his penance, and ſo his Non-performance of penance will paſs away in the Crowd of his other Sins, and there is an end of it. And if this pleaſe them not, there is an eaſier way ſtill, if need be: For you may get another man to do your penance for you. Is not this a fine eaſie way to Heaven, when the faſting and ſtarving of the Poor may be made to ſerve for a ſatisfaction for the Sins and Debauchery of the Rich? Indeed <hi>Eſcobar</hi> from <hi>Suarez,</hi> ſays, There ought to be a <hi>juſt Cauſe</hi> for one's performing penance for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But here the other Diſtinction will help them, <hi>non ad valorem, ſed ad juſtitiam requiritur cauſa,</hi> the penance is valid, though there be no juſt Cauſe. And whether there be a <hi>Cauſe</hi> or no, it is not doubted, ſays <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> but one may perform the penance for another, if the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor will give leave:</hi> And it is to be hoped there are ſome good natur'd Confeſſors to be found: But good Cardinal
<note n="*" place="margin">Tolet In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. Lib. 3. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Tolet</hi> is more free and generous than <hi>Eſcobar</hi> himſelf in this point: For he tells the Confeſſor, <hi>That he muſt impoſe a lighter Penance, if he ſees the Penitent will not perform a harder,</hi> without ever telling the Penitent, that this <hi>lighter</hi> will not ſerve his turn, or without ever putting him in mind of his Danger, or of the neceſſity of a <hi>harder</hi> penance; and wholly commits it to the prudence of one Prieſt to diminiſh the penance which another had impoſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as once telling him, that perhaps this penance will not ſuffice. So that in plain terms, by Conſequence, he reſolves it all into the power of the Prieſt; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59271:23"/>Confeſſor nor Penitent are any further accountable that I perceive, if too ſlight a penance be enjoyned, the Sin is pardoned notwithſtanding. And laſtly, he goes on, and ſhews, that though the Penitent be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perform his penance in his own perſon, yet he may transfer this to another, <hi>without his Confeſſor's leave;</hi> and yet he ſhall obtain the <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> part of penance, though not the <hi>meritorious,</hi> that is, he <hi>ſhall be excus'd from ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> evil; but ſhall not <hi>merit</hi> much at God's Hands by ſuch penance. And indeed I think he is very unreaſonable if he expect more: And beſides all this, the deſign of all penance being only to ſatisfie the Debt of Temporal puniſhment due to their Sins, there are ſeveral eaſie ways provided by their Church for the diſcharge of it, beſides the ſevere penance, as <hi>e. g.</hi> ſeveral ſhort Prayers, to the ſaying of which ſome ſcores of thouſands of years pardon are annexed, <hi>toties quoties;</hi> there are large Indulgences granted at <hi>Jubilees,</hi> and at ſeveral other good Times; and may at any time be had for a good Sum of Money; And if a man take no Care of himſelf all his Life, yet if he can purchaſe Prayers to be ſaid for him after his death, it will ſerve as well. And though the Penance be never ſo eaſie, and be performed as triflingly, yet the Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, by which they ſuppoſe the Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, by which they ſuppoſe the Debt of eternal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is diſcharged, muſt be as compleat and full as poſſible: For ſo the afore-named Cardinal, with a great deal of Concern, takes Care that the Abſolution be not pronounced <hi>conditionally,</hi> as <hi>e. g.</hi> on condition that you <hi>amend your Life,</hi> or <hi>perform your penance,</hi> &amp;c. but it muſt be pronounced abſolutely, without any <hi>if</hi> or <hi>and,</hi> thus, <hi>I abſolve thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now would not any one think, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by this Method of Confeſſions and Penances ſo taught and practiſed among them, rather deſigns to find out the Temper and Inclinations of people, and to dive
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59271:23"/>into the Councils of great Men, or to anſwer ſome other ſuch politick End, than to advance piety towards God, or Amendment of Life in the Penitent? I am ſure they can have no hearty reſpect for <hi>Devotion,</hi> when they are taught to look on their Prayers to God, as a ſevere Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and yet which they may be releaſed from by winning a Game at Cards, as is too commonly known.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And their Doctrine concerning the <hi>Merit of good Works</hi> and <hi>Supererogation,</hi> as it is falſe, ſo we cannot look on it as any Encouragement to Devotion; for God will not be ſerved with a Lye.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, if what is required of Men in their <hi>Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Penances</hi> be enough to ſave their Souls, they may very eaſily do more than is required: For they cannot do leſs, if they do any thing, though indeed one would wonder, that any that conſider the Nature of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or the Words of our Saviour, ſhould ever pretend to ſupererogate.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing their Doctrine to be true in theſe points, they cannot be thought to advance Devotion, but rather hinder it: For ſeeing it is ſome what natural for a Man to love his own Eaſe, every one will be apt to argue with himſelf, that ſo many have <hi>merited</hi> already, that there is no need of what he can do. Nay, it is Folly for him to attempt it: For what need he endeavour to add to a Stock of Merit, which is already infinite, as ſome have thought?</p>
            <p>And indeed it had need be infinite, elſe it is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is almoſt, if not quite ſpent, eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vaſt Expence of theſe Merits in frequent <hi>Jubilees,</hi> and other Indulgences, the Multitude of Sinners, and the little extraordinary Vertue and Piety found among them at this day, to add to their Store: So that methinks it may juſtly be queſtion'd whether they are not bankrupt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59271:24"/>before now, their Disburſement ſo much exceeding their Receipts; and the Credit of their Bank ſeems to depend wholly on their <hi>Old ſtock</hi> of Merit which the Ancients laid up for them; and yet they grant that this was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſual, than out of Deſign or good Nature: For the Saints deſign'd only to make ſure of doing enough for themſelves; and it ſeems that leſs ſerved their turns than they thought of, and the reſt was laid by for the uſe of ſuch rich Sinners as the Church would ſell it to. So that all this Stock of Merit, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſo great occaſion for, and of which there is made ſo prodigious an Expence, is at the beſt but a Chance and ſpare-heap, which they cannot tell how they came by (for every Biſhop hath the ſame Title to ſuch <hi>Treaſure-trove</hi> that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath,) nay, they have reaſon to fear there was never any ſuch Treaſure: (For I doubt not but the Saints in Heaven will thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully own, that they have received more from God than they deſerved, or could challenge:) to be ſure, they knew not how much there was ever laid up, nor whether the Stock be ſpent; and yet they ſpend as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now, as if they had been only laying up till this time, and that the Treaſure were now firſt opened.</p>
            <p>Many other ſuch Abſurdities and unanſwerable Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties there are in their Doctrine of <hi>Merit,</hi> and in their practiſe of applying theſe <hi>Merits</hi> to the uſe of others. And is it not a diſmal thing, that the Prieſts of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould teach men to truſt in, and as to Salvation, depend aſſuredly on theſe, of which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have no manner of Aſſurance nor Ground to hope. Is not this to play with Men's Souls and Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And eſpecially can this be urged as an Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Devotion, when, if it were as true as it is falſe, it tends directly to make Men vicious, and to neglect <hi>Devotion:</hi> For ſo a Man will think if there be ſuch a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59271:24"/>Stock in the Church, why ſhould not he have a Share of it as well as another? And if one can merit for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, why ſhould not he depend on others, as well as, they on his <hi>Merits?</hi> And ſeeing Merits may be bought as the <hi>Roman</hi> Caſuiſts have adjudged, he may think it very reaſonable that other's Merits ſhould be given him in exchange for his Money. So the Reſult of all is this, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Doctrine, and the ſuppoſed <hi>Church-ſtock,</hi> only one thing is needful, and that is <hi>Money;</hi> and this will <hi>fully make</hi> up all lack of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. And the belief of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and of the validity of <hi>Prayers for the dead,</hi> is no proper Encouragement of <hi>true Devotion:</hi> For <hi>true Devotion</hi> is ſuch as we perform to God, agreeably to his Will, when we know what we do, and for what ends, and have a promiſe or hope of Succeſs; but when a man prays to God to deliver a Soul out of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> he muſt ſuppoſe as true ſeveral things, which are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe, or at leaſt very uncertain; ſo that he can never pray in <hi>Faith,</hi> or without great perplexity and diſtraction of mind; for he knows not whether there be any ſuch place or ſtate as <hi>Purgatory:</hi> For Scripture ſays nothing of it, nor the Fathers of the three or four firſt Centuries. He knows not whether the Soul that he prays for be in <hi>Purgatory</hi> (if there ſhould be ſuch a place) for it may be in Heaven or in Hell, for ought he can tell. And if the Soul be in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> he knows not whether it be Uſeful or Lawful to pray for it; for God hath given us neither Command, nor Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor Liberty ſo to do, Nay, there are ſeveral particulars which they themſelves cannot agree on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Purgatory, viz.</hi> What Sins are promiſed there? How the Soul without its Body can be tormented there with a material Fire? Who are Gods Inſtruments in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Souls there? For the Devils are not; and how the Pope by his Indulgences can apply the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59271:25"/>of Chriſt and of the Saints ſo as to deliver any Soul out of <hi>Purgatory?</hi> And if there be ſuch a place, the Pope himſelf by his Example doth enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten all Men from endeavouring to deliver the Souls of their Friends from thence: For it is not doubted but he can deliver all out of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> he having the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Treaſure of the Church. And it muſt needs be a wonderful Diſcouragement to a Devout Mind, that among ſo many hundred Popes, there ſhould not be one found ſo Charitable as to releaſe ſo many thouſands of poor Souls that lye under intolerable pains, and ſo muſt lye till the laſt day, or till the debt of their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment be paid. If the Pope can do ſo much with ſo little Charge or Trouble to himſelf, and yet will not do it, ſurely I have leſs Reaſon to do any thing.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it follow, that becauſe it is a part of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable <hi>Devotion,</hi> for one Man to pray for another, whilſt living here on Earth; that therefore it is as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, for us to pray for Souls departed: For our Prayers for others on Earth, are either for Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bleſſings, or for the <hi>means of Grace.</hi> We pretend not to deſire God to reverſe his own Laws, and ſave ſuch a Man, let him be as bad as he will; but to make him <hi>Holy</hi> firſt, and then to make him <hi>Happy:</hi> And to Pray any otherwiſe for another Man, naturally tends to repreſent it as feaſible to reconcile a wicked Life with the hopes of Heaven; but when a Man is dead he can Work no more, nor make any uſe of the <hi>means of Grace,</hi> and therefore there is no room for this Prayer to God for him, he is not capable of <hi>Repentance, and Glory, and Amendment,</hi> and of being made fit for Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If they boaſt of the <hi>validity of the Orders</hi> of their Biſhops and Prieſts, as an Encouragement to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, the validity of the Sacraments dependnig ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59271:25"/>much on the Legality of the Miniſtry; We anſwer that we have a Clergy as properly and truly of Chriſt's ſending as any Church in the World; againſt whoſe Ordination and Miſſion nothing can be objected: We deriving the Succeſſion of our Biſhops, not only from their own <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but from the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops before his time, which is the only Regular way of Miſſion, that we know of, except that of an extrarodinary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from Heav'n as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had. And I would not that there were that to be objected againſt us, that is juſtly objected againſt them, as to the Succeſſion of their Popes even ſince the Reformation began. For the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. was moſt notoriouſly Simoniacal, and yet one that comes by Simony into the Popedom, is by their own Canon Law, by the Bull or Conſtitution of <hi>Julius</hi> II. approved in the Council of <hi>Lateran, An.</hi> 1513. <hi>to be looked on as a Magician, Heathen, Publican,
<note place="margin">Septimi Decretal, Lib. 1. Tit. 3.</note> and Arch-Heretick, and his Election can never be made valid by any after Act,</hi> and yet ſeveral of the Popes ſince, were either made Cardinals by this <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. or received that Dignity from thoſe that received it from him; which is the very Caſe of this preſent Pope <hi>Innocent Eleventh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> it is plain that they have more diviſions among themſelves, then they can charge us with. For they have not only ſuch as openly diſſent and ſeparate from them, but great and violent diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among their own Members, and ſuch as live in the Communion of their Church, one againſt another, and each party pleads the Doctrine of the Church, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of its Councils. And yet the Pope himſelf, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Infallibility and Authority, either cannot or dare not determine which is in the Right, or which Opinion is True.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:59271:26"/>
            <p> So that whatever <hi>Power and Authority</hi> their Church hath, it hath no good effect to ſuch ends and purpoſes, to which Church-Power is deſigned to ſerve, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of Holineſs and Vertue, and the diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing of Vice, the Preſervation of the Doctrine in Purity, and of the Members at peace one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is true they are more able to ſee the Laws of their Church Duly executed; but it is to their diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to have ſo much Power, and yet to do ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good with it. As for us, we had rather deſerve more then we have, then that it ſhould be ſaid that we have more power then we deſerve. And whatever Power our Church wants, and whatever loſs Religion ſuffers by this means, we juſtly Charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the guilt of it, who have made all Princes jealous, and affraid of all Church-Power, by their invading their temporal Rights under pretence of a Spiritual Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, though ſomewhat may be ſaid for the worſt thing, and a very bad Cauſe may have a great deal plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in its Vindication, as we have ſeen in all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Helps and Inſtances of Devotion, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſts of; yet if we conſider them, they all in ſome reſpect or other come ſhort of what they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to; ſeveral of them being very improper, many plainly Nonſenſical and Ridiculous; they proceed from bad Principles, are done in an undue Manner and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or to ſerve ſome bad end or deſign, or ſome ſuch other way offend; even the moſt ſecure Practices, which moſt reſemble true Self-denial, are countenanced or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned rather to make a ſhow, or to gratifie ſome Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, then to advance Devotion; for exceſſes and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actings are often Infirmities, and the effects of Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſteddineſs being the moſt certain ſign of Strength, as the ſhaking Palſy is a Diſeaſe and Sign of Weakneſs, as well as the <hi>Dead one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59271:26"/> 3. I now come to conſider ſuch things in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as tend directly to promote Debauchery of Manners, and Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs in Devotion.</p>
            <p>I'll inſiſt only on theſe few, among very many.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The unlimited Power which they aſcribe to the Church, or to the Pope as Head or Monarch of it: For the People are taught that he can make null Duties that were made neceſſary by God, and make neceſſary what was not ſo before. The Conſequence of which Doctrine is plainly this, that a Man may ſafely diſobey and neglect the ſerving of God, if he pay but his due reſpects to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And yet their Caſuiſts have defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the Pope can diſpenſe with Sins, or give leave to do things forbidden by the law of God, as well as pardon them when committed, as in the Diſpenſations with <hi>unlawful Marriages.</hi> And on the other ſide he can excuſe them from doing what they are by their Duty to God bound to do, as in his Diſpenſations with <hi>Vows</hi> though made never ſo ſolemnly to God himſelf. That is, he can bind where God hath left us looſe, and he can looſe where God has bound us. Nay, a Superiour can give a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> even when he doubteth whether it be lawful or no; <hi>becauſe in a doubtful caſe the milder ſide is to be taken.</hi> And if the Reaſon ceaſeth for which the Diſpenſation was given, yet the Diſpenſation doth not ceaſe: Nay, a Diſpenſation may be granted where there is no Reaſon or Cauſe for it; and yet the Diſpenſation is valid notwithſtanding. And not the Pope only, but every Biſhop and Prieſt hath his Share of this Power, only there are ſome <hi>reſerved</hi> and more profitable <hi>Caſes,</hi> which <hi>his Holineſs</hi> only can diſpenſe in. And though I cannot tell what they <hi>think,</hi> yet I am ſure their Caſuiſts are very ſhy of <hi>ſaying,</hi> that there is any Caſe in which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59271:27"/>there may not be a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> granted for the doing of it, or a Pardon for it when it is done.</p>
            <p>And all Indulgencies are directly deſigned to hinder Devotion, for they are given to free Men from the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Mortification, frequent Alms and Prayers,</hi> &amp;c. which elſe would have been enjoyned as Penance; and yet we know that theſe are the chiefeſt parts of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And as their general Doctrine concerning the validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Pardons and Indulgencies is very deſtructive of all true Piety and Religion: So,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their conſtant Practice of giving <hi>Abſolution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Penance,</hi> is in a more eſpecial manner influential to that purpoſe. For the People are taught to believe, that by the Prieſts ſaying, <hi>I abſolve thee,</hi> &amp;c. the Sin is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally pardoned by God: And though indeed their Guides of Confeſſors adviſe that Abſolution ſhould not be given till Penance be impoſed and accepted; yet when the Confeſſor thinks that the Penitent will accept of the Penance, he may abſolve him firſt: That is, the Perſon may be abſolved before he accept the Penance, or even promiſe to perform it; but it is their conſtant Method to abſolve him before Penance be actually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.</p>
            <p>Now if their Abſolution be of force, the Perſon is free from his Sin, and ſure enough of Heaven, whether he perform any Penance or no: Which Practice gives all imaginable Encouragement and Licenſe to Sin; the fear of Penance being the only reſtraint from Sin which they pretend to; but if the Sin be fully pardoned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Penance be accepted or performed: I ſee not why a man ſhould trouble himſelf much for the performance of his Penance; he ſees plainly that it is only an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix that is uſed to be annext to Abſolution, but is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary in it ſelf nor for Abſolution; the Sin is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59271:27"/>pardon'd already, and at the worſt there is only ſome temporal Puniſhment to be ſatisfied for, which he may get rid of ſeveral other ways.</p>
            <p>Nay indeed the true and ancient Notion of Penance is utterly deſtroyed, by its being impoſed and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after Abſolution. For Penance according to the Primitive uſe of it, was a ſevere courſe of Life preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to a Perſon that had grieviouſly offended, as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Method for him, at the ſame time to teſtifie his own ſorrow for his Sin, and abhorrence of it, and to create in him an Averſation to the Like for the time to come; and alſo to ſatisfie the Church of all this, that ſo he might be admitted to Abſolution and the Communion: And therefore their Penances were always publick, and indeed it is by publick Penance only that all theſe ſo good ends can poſſibly be anſwered: But now in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Offender is pardoned without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of this, he is not put to any grief for his Sin before he be abſolved. It is left wholly to his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Generoſity whether he will perform <hi>any Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> for his Sin. N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y indeed ſo loath are they to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſevere againſt Sin, or Cruel to the Sinner; that when in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſome would have revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this DIſcipline, by enacting <hi>publick Penance,</hi> they were violently oppoſed and over-ruled; tho St. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> a Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> had held it to be <hi>of Divine Right:</hi> and their Caſuiſts ſince teach that a Confeſſor cannot, or ought not to enjoyn a <hi>publick Penance:</hi> So that by this means a Man is not ſo much as to be put to the bluſh for his Sins; for no ſuch Penance muſt be impoſed by which the Sin may be known, and he is ſure that the Confeſſor to ſave a Kingdom dare not reveal or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Their Doctrine concerning the <hi>Nature of ſeveral Sins,</hi> is ſuch as muſt needs rather incourage Men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59271:28"/>in Sin, than deliver us from it; and will ſpoil all true Devotion to God, and that due regard that we ought to have to his Commandments.</p>
            <p>They tell us there is a vaſt number of Sins in their own Nature <hi>Venial,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſcobar Tract. 2. Exam. 1. cap. 4.</note> which are ſo very inconſiderable that an infinite number of them altogether will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive a man of the Grace and Favour of God, or make up one Mortal Sin, and for the Pardon of which there is no need or occaſion for the Mercy of God: And yet they have no certain Rules to diſcover whether a Sin be <hi>Mortal</hi> or <hi>Venial,</hi> ſo that men are in wonderful danger of being cheated in a matter of ſo great Moment as their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation.</p>
            <p>They tell us alſo,
<note place="margin">Eſcobar Tract. 2. Exam. 1. cap. 2.</note> that an <hi>Habitual Sin,</hi> is only a Stain left by former voluntary Sins, and a Deprivation of habitual Goodneſs; but hath nothing elſe that is evil in it. From which Doctrine it neceſſarily follows that a man is guilty only of thoſe Sins which created this <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> and that there is not an habitual Repentance, or Courſe of Life required to get pardon for habitual Sins; but a few or perhaps one ſingle Act of Contrition will ſerve. So that the more a Man ſinneth the better he may, and it is a piece of true Prudence to get an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of all Sin betimes; for a Man is accountable only for thoſe Sins which preceded the Habit; all the Sins which follow it will paſs under the name of <hi>Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencies,</hi> and as ſuch can be eſteemed only as a kind of <hi>Venial</hi> Sins.</p>
            <p>And they not only allow the Church Power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what doth not belong to her in many Cafes; but give ſuch Authority to her Commands, as to make the Diſobedience to them the greateſt of all Sins, and make way for the breaking of the Laws of God, that they may keep thoſe of the Church. So <hi>Marriage</hi> hath been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged a greater Sin in a Prieſt than <hi>Fornication,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59271:28"/>the Prieſts are oblig'd to <hi>Celibacy</hi> by the Laws of the Church, and their own Vow; as if they were not by the Laws of God, and their Vow of Baptiſm more obliged to abſtain from <hi>Fornication;</hi> and accordingly for <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> a Prieſt is excommunicated or depoſed; but for <hi>Fornication,</hi> he is only obliged to confeſs it ſecretly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his other Sins; and the Guilt and Irregularity of it is done away by Abſolution. Indeed they bring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Sins under the Head of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> not only by pretending to give Pardon and Diſpenſations for moſt Sins that can be committed; but alſo when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Sins, they are always moſt earneſt againſt ſuch as tranſgreſs the Commands of the Church. So <hi>v.g.</hi> when <hi>Eſcobar</hi> asks the Queſtion, <hi>What if I communicate unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily at</hi> Eaſter? He anſwers, <hi>That by ſo doing, I fulfil the Command of the Church, which is what I am immediately bound to:</hi> And paſſeth over the Duty of Self-examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Preparation ſo ſtrictly enjoyned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as not worthy to be conſidered: And ſo in innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſes; by which means indeed they create a great Veneration for the Church, or for that which they call the Church; but thereby make the Commands of God of none effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Their very Doctrine concerning their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Devotions, and their Practiſe conſequent on it, is ſuch as is altogether inconſiſtent with the Nature of true Devotion: For, according to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the outward Act will ſuffice in many Caſes, though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Mind go along with it; particularly as to Prayers <hi>Eſcobar</hi> from <hi>Coninch</hi> and <hi>Durandus</hi> affirms, that neither an actual, nor vertual Attention is required when a man <hi>prayeth;</hi> and they give an excellent Reaſon for what they ſay, <hi>viz. Becauſe the Church hath no Power in hidden Caſes, but only in the Caſe of Auricular Confeſſion:</hi> As if in Prayer only the power of the Church, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59271:29"/>to its Commands were to be regarded: And he confirmeth his Aſſertion with this other moſt cogent Compariſon, That an outward Act of Devotion, or Prayer only with the Mouth, is a true Act of Prayer, tho without the Intention, as an outward Act of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of an Idol, though without the Intention, is a true Act of Idolatry. So that for a man to mind what he doth when he is at Prayers, or to be earneſt in his Deſires of that which he prayeth for, though it may poſſibly be a Commendation, and Accompliſhment, yet it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary either to the pleaſing of God, or ſatisfying of his Duty according to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nay, it is a praiſe for a man to <hi>draw nigh with the Mouth, and honour him with the Lips, though the Heart be far from God,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that our Saviour, after the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> blamed the <hi>Jews</hi> for ſo doing. Indeed ſuch a kind of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial Chriſtians will this Doctrine make, that a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee</hi> would have been an excellent Man, if he had lived in theſe days.</p>
            <p>And purſuant to this Doctrine of the No neceſſity of Attention at Prayers, they take care that the people ſhall not be able to attend to what is done; and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide that the <hi>publick Prayers</hi> and the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf ſhall be only in a <hi>Language unknown</hi> to the people, and are ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately found of this Device of keeping the people ignorant of what is prayed for, that their Caſuiſts have defined, that a Man may ſay his <hi>Office</hi> privately in other Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beſides the <hi>Latin,</hi> as in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> or <hi>Greek,</hi> but not in the Vulgar Language; at the ſame time keeping the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Ignorance, and diſcouraging them in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and exerciſing their Authority over them in the moſt dangerous manner that can be.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Their aſcribing ſpiritual Effects to ſeveral things which are purely of their own Invention, is much to the Diſcouragement of true Devotion towards God. And
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59271:29"/>yet they have very many things of this Nature: As <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Water,</hi> by the being ſprinkled with which, they believe the Devil ſhall have leſs power over them: <hi>Agnus Dei's, Swords</hi> and <hi>Medals</hi> which they wear to preſerve them from Dangers; which being conſecrated according to the Rules of their Church, have through the Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Perſons, and the power of the Church, a wonderful good effect, though indeed God never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>To this Head I may refer alſo, their <hi>Roſary,</hi> which is nothing elſe but an odd Combination of <hi>Pater-noſter</hi>'s and <hi>Ave Mary</hi>'s. Several <hi>ſhort Prayers</hi> to the ſaying of which thouſands of years of pardon of Sins are annext: Their carrying the Image of St. <hi>Genovefa</hi> in Proceſſion at <hi>Paris,</hi> and other Images in other Places to obtain Rain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and innumerable other ſuch like Practices, on which Men are taught to relie, and to expect great good by, though they have neither any natural force or efficacy that way; nor any aſſurance from God that ſuch effects ſhall follow. Nay even the <hi>Sacraments</hi> themſelves according to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are only ſuch a kind of <hi>Charms;</hi> for they are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to work effectually on the Perſon, without any Devotion or Vertuous Diſpoſition being required of him in order to it.</p>
            <p>Now whatever effect they promiſe above what the natural efficacy of the thing is apt and able to produce, they muſt have expreſs Authority from God, or elſe they ſadly delude and cheat thoſe poor Souls that depend upon them. And at the beſt they are ſuppoſed only a ſhorter cut to Heaven, an eaſier way of pleaſing God and getting his Bleſſing, and are invented only to eaſe a Man of the fatigue and trouble of the common and ordinary rode of ſerving <hi>him</hi> by a conſtancy and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of Devotions.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:59271:30"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Their Manuals and Books of Devotion which they give their People to read, inſtead of the Scripture which they forbid to be uſed, though they may deſign them as <hi>Helps,</hi> yet I muſt range them among the <hi>Hindrances</hi> of <hi>Devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the beſt of them are ſo full of Tautologies and vain Repetitions, that they muſt needs come under the Cenſure of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. though they uſe his own holy Name. For ſo in the <hi>Jeſus Pſalter,</hi> at the end of the <hi>Manual of Prayers and Litanies Printed at</hi> Paris <hi>in Engliſh,</hi> An. 1682. in a Litany of fifteen Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, the Name <hi>Jeſu</hi> is repeated over above 130 times. And in the ſame Book, in the <hi>Litany of the bleſſed Virgin,</hi> they pray to her by 40 ſeveral Names, being only ſo many diſtinct praiſes of her. And the like is obſervable in all their Books of Devotion which I ever ſaw. Now their ſaying the ſame thing ſo often over, is not contrived to help and aſſiſt Attention, or prevent Diſtraction, or as a Repetition of what is more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily important, or for any other good and prudent Reaſon, but out of pure Vanity and Oſtentation, or as it were even to flatter our bleſſed Saviour or the Saint which they pray to.</p>
            <p>But moſt of the Books and Legends which they put into the hands of their People to excite their Devotion, and by which the People take an eſtimate of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, are ſuch wretched plain Forgeries, and ſo pitifully contrived Fables, as can never be believed by Men of Senſe, and if they could be believed, are proper indeed to make Men Mad and Enthuſiaſtical, but not to advance true Devotion; and he that reads only ſuch Books is qualified indeed to tell Stories and to believe Lies, but no ſerious truth will ſtick to him or be valued by him. So that ſuch Books as theſe are ſo far from doing good, that they do much harm to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59271:30"/>for they Imprint a wrong Notion of Religion on Mens Minds; would make a Man believe that God is like a Child pleaſed with Trifles, that Religion and the Method of our Salvation is only a Charm and Trick, which the Prieſts have gotten the receit of; but that there is nothing in Chriſtianity fit to make a man wife and manly in his Worſhip of God, or in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelf and practice of Devotion. Nay the Stories which are told in the Lives of their Saints, and believed by the Common People, are enough even to deprave the natural Sentiments of Mankind concerning God and Religion, ſo that perhaps it were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to leave Men to the natural effluxes of their own minds, than to pretend to aſſiſt them with ſuch Helps as theſe. That a little <hi>Water</hi> or a <hi>conſecrated Bell</hi> ſhould ſcare the Devil, or St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s rope charm and bind him, would make a Man have little fear of ſuch an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or a prodigious Veneration for ſuch a Saint; but how it ſhould render a Man more piouſly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, more relying on his Providence, or more Religiouſly Careful over himſelf, I ſee not: And theſe Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries though ſo apparently falſe, yet being affirm'd with ſuch Confidence, ſtrike at the very Foundation of our Religion; For it is apt to make Men believe that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity it ſelf was at firſt propagated among a ſad dull ſtupid and credulous Generation of Men; (when as really it firſt appeared in an Age as ſharp-ſighted, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Age before or ſince, which is much for its Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.) It would tempt a Man to deſpiſe a Religion in which ſuch Men are <hi>Saints,</hi> and ſuch Practiſes commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; And will ſet Chriſtianity but on the ſame level with modern <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Mahometaniſm;</hi> For the <hi>Jews</hi> have juſt as much to ſay for their <hi>Cabbala,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> for their incredible <hi>Fables;</hi> for they are reported on the ſame Credit, are juſt ſo credible in themſelves, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59271:31"/>juſt as edifying of the People that attend to them: The Miracles which they relate being often Juſt ſo uſeful, as that pretended to be wrought in the Temple of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo;</hi> when a Man coming out of the Temple, it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that his body did not caſt any ſhadow; by which thing however ſtrange in it ſelf, the Man was not much the better, nor the World wiſer.</p>
            <p>But many of their Books of Devotion are worſe than ridiculous; for there are frequently ſuch paſſages and prayers as I cannot tell how to vindicate from <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy</hi> and <hi>Idolatry. Saint Bonaventure</hi>'s <hi>Pſalter</hi> both in <hi>Latin,</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> I mentioned before, in which there are I believe a thouſand ſuch Prayers to her, or Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions concerning her, which I confeſs I could not with a ſafe Conſcience ſay of any Creature. And <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> the Maſter of St <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> hath not only 12 Books of the Praiſes of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> but alſo a diſtinct Book called <hi>Biblia Mariana;</hi> in which he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies ſeveral places of Scripture to the <hi>Virgin Mary;</hi> as if ſhe were prefigured in ſeveral paſſages of the Old Teſtament as well as her Son: So <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>that ſhe was that Heaven that God made.</hi> Gen. 1.3. <hi>She was the Light which God there made;</hi> and ſo on through almoſt the whole Scripture: And however Cautious they are in the Books which they Print in Engliſh for the uſe of their Converts here: yet in them we find often ſuch ſayings to or of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> as I cannot reconcile with Chriſtianity; for ſo in the <hi>Manual</hi> quoted before, in the Prayers for Women with Child they ſing thus to her,
<q>
                  <l>Hail to the Queen who Reigns above,</l>
                  <l>Mother of Clemencie and Love, &amp;c.</l>
               </q> Elſewhere they pray thus to her, <hi>pag.</hi> 196. Obleſſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59271:31"/>Mother <hi>aſſiſt my Weakneſs in all my Dangers and Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in all Temptations to Sin, and in the hour of my Death, that through thy Protection I may be ſafe in the Lord.</hi> Where the <hi>Lord</hi> indeed is mentioned, out of Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for Faſhions ſake, but they had firſt begged of the <hi>Lady</hi> as much as they wanted or could deſire: <hi>and pag.</hi> 80. they call her <hi>Spouſe of the Holy Ghoſt, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Prophets, Expectation of the Patriarchs, Queen of the Angels, Teacher of the Apoſtles, Strengthner of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Faithful Comforter of the Living and Dead.</hi> Now if they Print ſuch things in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> what do they Print in <hi>Spaniſh? If they do ſuch things in a Green Tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> And I fear that even their ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Caſuiſts give too much Countenance to this ſo groſs Practice: For they have determined that <hi>Honour's above Civil, cuitus Hyperduliae</hi> are due to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> that is in plain Engliſh, <hi>Divine Honours</hi> muſt be paid to her. For it muſt be a very Metaphyſical Head, that can in this Senſe apprehend a kind of Honour above <hi>Civil,</hi> and yet not <hi>Divine;</hi> it muſt be ſomewhat like his, that would pretend to find a mean between <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>Creature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Finite and Infinite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, this is moſt notorious, that they enjoyn acts to be uſed, and propoſe Objects of Worſhip which they themſelves cannot deny but there is danger of offending in them, and even of falling into that Idolatry; and yet take little or no care of giving caution concerning them; and if the groſſeſt abuſe ſhould happen, there is ſcarcely any poſſibility of redreſs.</p>
            <p>Indeed wherever they ſpeak of Veneration due to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques and Images, of worſhipping of Saints, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> they always ſeem as if they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not how much Honour were paid to them; only they muſt make as if they put ſome Reſtriction on it, for the ſake of the reformed who would exclaim againſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59271:32"/>them: And therefore their Command for the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them is general and abſolute; but the Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſo nice and forced, that one may eaſily ſee that they very unwillingly deny any Worſhip to be paid to them. For ſo the wary Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> ſays, They are to be <hi>kept, and due Honour and Veneration paid to them:</hi> And though by and by they ſeem as if they would limit this Honour, yet preſently they put in ſuch words as make that pretended Limitation to ſignifie nothing: For they tell you, That <hi>whatever Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor you pay to the Image, goes to the perſon repreſented,</hi> (v. g. to our Saviour) it ſeems the Honor is paid to him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we intend ſo or no: And hence you may eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what Honor is due to the Image of our Saviour, and how little fear there is of paying too much Honour to it: For I ſuppoſe we are all agreed there is no fear of paying too much Honour to our Bleſſed Saviour; and whatever Honour is paid to his Image, is paid to him, if we can believe theſe Gentlemen. And agreeably here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, it is very rare to hear of any perſon cenſured or blamed for paying too much Honour to Images, though ſurely it is as poſſible for men to be Idolaters now as in the former Ages; and I ſuppoſe that neither the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, nor all the Prieſts are Men of ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Underſtanding and Learning, as to be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free from the like Temptation. Nay, the Caution which is given ſeems only to concern, <hi>Imagines falſi dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis, &amp; Rudibus periculoſi Erroris Occaſionem praebentes;</hi> but there is not one word concerning the abuſe which may be made of the Image of Chriſt, or of a true Saint: There is no Proviſion made that Men be warned not to perform too much Devotion in their Minds to a good I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            <p>And by what this Council ſays the Prieſt underſtands well enough what it intends; and therefore ſcarcely ever
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59271:32"/>dare preach againſt the exceſs and abuſe of Images, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tho they cannot but ſee it actually commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every day.</p>
            <p>And now if there ſhould happen to be any Idolatrous Worſhip pay'd to an Image; tho the Biſhop hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er indeed to ſet the Image up, yet he hath not power to pull it down, or to correct any abuſe concerning it; without the leave of the Archbiſhop and other Biſhops of the Province, and even of the Pope himſelf. So unwilling do they ſeem that any Proviſion ſhould be made for redreſſing abuſes in ſo great and common a Caſe as the exceſs in Worſhip of Images muſt needs be, <hi>v. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> as we have ſeen how deficient and very faulty the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is in her pretences to Devotion, wee'll now conſider what Proviſion is made for the due Exerciſe of Devotion <hi>among our ſelves;</hi> that we may thank God for our being ſettled in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and may learn to be conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſtrict and regular in our own, as well as to deſpiſe the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Devotions. And in order hereunto, I rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon that theſe four things are eſpecially to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That among us none but the true Object of Devotion is propoſed to be worſhipped. God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son and Holy Ghoſt, none of the moſt bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or Saints in Heaven being ever invoked, or ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by us. For we look on them only as our Brethren, and Members of the ſame Church with us, triumphing indeed whilſt we are here below ſtill in our Warfare. We thank God for them, and keep Feaſts in the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, at the ſame time praiſing God for his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Grace beſtowed on them, and ſhining forth in them, and alſo ſtirring up our ſelves by ſuch Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morations to follow their good Example, and this we
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59271:33"/>think is as much as is due from us to our fellow Creatures, and believe that neither God allows, nor do they expect more from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Only <hi>proper Expreſſions of Devotion</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or allowed by our Church. For the matter of them they are ſuch as God himſelf hath required to be ſerved by, are ſignificant of that diſpoſition of Mind which we know God accepts, and have an aptneſs to the producing of that temper in us which God intends to work us up to by them: We uſe all the Inſtances of Devotion which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> uſe, if they be either neceſſary or fit; though indeed often to other and better purpoſe. We <hi>pray</hi> conſtantly, but only for the <hi>living;</hi> for we look on the <hi>Dead</hi> as paſt the means of Grace, and conſequently paſt the benefit of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. We <hi>praiſe</hi> God for his Excellencies in himſelf, and <hi>thank</hi> him for his Goodneſs to others as well as to our ſelves: We practiſe <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of Sins to God in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and in private, and adviſe it to be made alſo to the Miniſters of Gods Word, when it is neceſſary for Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Counſel and Advice, for the ſatisfying of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the removal of Scruple, and Doubtfulneſs: but we cannot ſay it is neceſſary to be made to <hi>Men</hi> in order to the Pardon of <hi>God:</hi> We reckon it rather as a priviledg or advantage than a Duty? And if Men will not make uſe of this priviledg, as often as there is Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion unleſs we tell a lye to advance the credit of it, we cannot help that: We enjoyn <hi>Faſtings</hi> and diſallow not of <hi>Penances,</hi> but adviſe People to take an holy revenge on themſelves when they have ſinned; but not as the Papiſts do to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> for their Sins, or <hi>merit</hi> at Gods hand, but to ſhew the ſincerity of their Repentance, and to ſtrengthen their Reſolutions of amendment; for it is our amendment, and not our puniſhment which God is pleaſed with. And we take care that all theſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59271:33"/>things be performed in a due meaſure, proportionably to the ſtrength of the Perſon, and the Nature and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Duty; but are afraid of ſtraining them too high, leſt men ſhould be altogether deterred from them, or acquieſce only in the outward Action, or render our ſelves and our Cauſe ridiculous by an imprudent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement. We have the Sacraments duly adminiſtred, as our Saviour commanded them; we reckon our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with Water perfect without Oyl or Spittle: We grutch not the Cup to the Laity, nor celebrate ſolitary Communions, nor admire whiſpering to God in the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; but as we have received from Chriſt, ſo we teach and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, without Addition or Diminution of any thing eſſential or material. In ſhort, in the holy Offices them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the behaviour which our Church requires they be celebrated with, there is always a great proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty obſervable, agreeable to the Command of God in Scripture, and the Practice of the Apoſtles and firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church, proper to the ſeveral parts of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, expreſſive of our Senſe, conſonant to Reaſon, and the uſe of the World, eſpecially reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always had to the exciting of Piety and Devotion in the minds and carriage of our People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All uſeful Helps, Motives and Occaſions are here plentifully afforded and preſſed on Men. For we not only have all our Service in a Language which the meaneſt People underſtand, but have it ſo contrived by frequent Reſponſes, that every Perſon bears a part in that Worſhip which he is ſo much concerned in, and doth not only hear the Prieſt ſpeak to God Almighty, but prays for himſelf, and is required to joyn his aſſent to every ſhort Prayer by a diſtinct <hi>Amen.</hi> With us the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Rules of Life are enjoyned to all, all Men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame Concern in another Life however differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59271:34"/>their Circumſtances and Cocerns are in this Life. We have conſtant Prayers in every Pariſh weekly at leaſt, in many dayly, with the bleſſed Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt frequently adminiſtred, nay every <hi>Sunday,</hi> not only in Cathedrals, but in ſeveral Colledges and private Pariſh Churches. And we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all Men whether there be any where more practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sermons, fitted to the Caſes of Men, without Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Superſtition, than among us; Whether good and free Learning be any where more encouraged, or where better care is taken for the due Inſtruction of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: The Scriptures being in every one's hands, with us, and other excellent Books made according to the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures, inſtead of Legends and Lives of Saints, St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi>'s <hi>Pſalter,</hi> and other ſuch Books which are really Libels againſt Chriſtianity, and yet are the principal Books which the Prieſts of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> commend to their People: For as for the Bible, if any one of them hath happened to read in it, who is not licenſed to that purpoſe, he muſt own it as a Sin to his Prieſt at his next Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>And as there are ſuch bleſſed Opportunities afforded ſo conſtantly, and ſuch Prudent Proviſion made for all Caſes Ordinary and Extraordinary, ſo I thank God, we can ſay that our People are generally very diligent in the uſe of theſe Means; (or would be more ſo, were it not for the Diviſions which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> eſpecially raiſe among us.) For they may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that we urge no more on them than their own good, and the commands of God require of them; though our Church knows her Power very well, yet ſhe makes uſe of it only to enforce the Laws of God, to explain, illuſtrate and apply them to particular Caſes, but never to ſet up her own Commands in Oppoſition to them, as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59271:34"/>the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth; and therefore though we teach our People to dread an Excommunication, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſummum futuri Judicii Praejudicium,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls it, <hi>a foretaſt or foreſtalling of the laſt Judgment;</hi> and not for a World to lye under it, though it were inflicted only for Contempt; yet we warn them in the firſt place to avoid the Cauſe and Occaſion of Excommunication, and therefore not to value what Cenſures of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> we are under, they being ſo very unjuſt and Groundleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> as only the true <hi>Object of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is here worſhipped, only <hi>proper Expreſſions</hi> allowed, all <hi>uſeful Helps</hi> afforded; ſo alſo the <hi>greateſt ſtreſs is laid on the Practiſe of it,</hi> agreeable to the true Nature, End and Deſign of it. The Principal ends of Devotion are to pay a Homage to God our great Creator and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, to get his Bleſſing, and to work our ſelves up to a better temper of Mind: And to this end we are in our Service Importunate without Vanity or Impertinency, long without Tediouſneſs, or Idle Repetitions; (Only we uſe the Lord's Prayer often, that no part of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may be without that perfect form, and alſo in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the great Comprehenſiveneſs of it, and of the Diſtraction of Men's Minds which ſeldom can attend to the full Senſe of it all at one time.) And we teach our People that every Man muſt work for himſelf, for he that prays only by a Proxy, it is very juſt that he ſhould be rewarded only by a Proxy too; we put our People in mind that an unfeigned Repentance is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Neceſſary, and not a Verbal one only: That it is out of our power, and of any Man's in the World to turn <hi>Attrition</hi> into Contrition. We pretend not to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe</hi> with any for not obeying the Command of God. We have no <hi>Taxa Camaerae</hi> by which the Papiſts are ſhown
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59271:35"/>how all Sins are fined in their Church; for in that Book Men ſee at what Charge they may kill a Father, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Inceſt with their Siſters: But we aſſure all, that <hi>the Wages of Sin is Death,</hi> Death Eternal, if indulged and not moſt earneſtly repented of. And we tell all that Devotion is neceſſary for all, though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ways of gratifying every Inclination, ſo as they that will not lead a ſtrict Life, need not, and yet may have hopes of Salvation: We own their Policy in this Contrivance, but do not ſo much admire their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious regard to the Salvation of Mens Souls.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, though we thus forcibly preſs all Chriſtian Duties on all Men; yet at the ſame time we warn them not to pretend to Merit Heaven at God's Hand; but after they have done their beſt, to confeſs they are <hi>unprofitable Servants.</hi> Werſay of our Charity or whatever elſe we do in Obedience to God, that <hi>of his own we give to him,</hi> and we are bound to thank him both for the Will and the Ability to give. The moſt that we pretend to, is only to make a ſmall Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment by way of Sacrifice for what we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; we beg of God to accept it as a Teſtimony of a grateful Mind, and we know that his Goodneſs is ſo great, that he will abundantly reward an honeſt and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Servant, though he hath done no more than was his Duty: And we hope that what we offer though mingled with many Imperfections, he will be pleaſed to accept for the ſake of Chriſt as if it were perfect.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Grounds that we go on in our Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and whatever we do for the Honour of God; and thus deſigning and thus acting and perſiſting, we need not doubt but the good Providence of God which watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59271:35"/>over his whole Church, will in an eſpecial manner watch over this which is ſo pure a Member of it; that he will accept of the Devotions which are offered to him in it, and hear the Prayers that are made unto him for it, and defend it againſt all its Enemies on every ſide; which God of his Infinite Mercy grant for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
